<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>XMPP</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="/feeds/ralphm.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2007-02-01T09:01:00+01:00</updated><entry><title>Presence at FOSDEM</title><link href="/2007/02/presence-at-fosdem" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2007-02-01T09:01:00+01:00</updated><author><name>ralphm</name></author><id>tag:,2007-02-01:2007/02/presence-at-fosdem</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.fosdem.org/" title="Free and Open source Software Developers' Europe Meeting"&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt;, the Free and Open source Software Developers' Europe Meeting, is an annual two-day conference held in Brussels, Belgium. This year the event will take place on 24 and 25 February. It is a large event with 22 main track talks, 25 lightning talks, 20 booths, and 14 developers' rooms. Developers' rooms are centered around a particular project or interest group and can be used for giving presentations and tutorials, discussion, etc., resulting in an additional 146 slots in 2006. While there is no entrance fee, FOSDEM is funded by the generous donations of its 2000+ visitors and several sponsors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like previous years, the Jabber/XMPP community is represented by a booth and a developers' room. Also, &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/people/stpeter.shtml"&gt;Peter Saint-Andre&lt;/a&gt; will talk about &lt;a href="http://fosdem.org/2007/schedule/events/jabber"&gt;Secure Communications with Jabber&lt;/a&gt; in the Internet Services track, and most of the members of the XMPP Council and XSF Board will be present throughout the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In December I &lt;a href="http://ralphm.net/blog/2006/11/17/fosdem_2007_call" title="FOSDEM call for presence"&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; a Call for Presence for presentations in our developers' room. I received a number of very interesting abstracts, but there is still room for a handful of presentations. With our community growing like it is, there must be plenty of projects that could present how they use XMPP in their work. We are thinking about slots of 45 minutes, with 30 minutes of presentation and then some time for questions and discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have an interesting project that you want to talk about and get exposure for before a mostly technical audience, drop me a line with a short abstract. The deadline for submission of our schedule is &lt;strong&gt;Saturday 3 February&lt;/strong&gt;, so contact me today or tomorrow!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also &lt;a href="http://wiki.jabber.org/index.php/FOSDEM_2007" title="Jabber presence at FOSDEM 2007"&gt;keep track&lt;/a&gt; of people that are planning to come to FOSDEM in our wiki. Be sure to add your name there!&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>