<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>XMPP</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="/feeds/stpeter.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 May 2014 12:16:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Happy Encrypted Network!</title><link>/2014/05/happy-encrypted-network</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today, a large number of services on the public XMPP network permanently turned on mandatory encryption for client-to-server and server-to-server connections (there's a fine summary &lt;a href="http://blog.prosody.im/mandatory-encryption-on-xmpp-starts-today/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first step toward making the XMPP network more secure for all users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for more updates as we work on ubiquitous authentication, secure DNS, end-to-end encryption, and other improvements.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 19 May 2014 12:16:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-05-19:2014/05/happy-encrypted-network</guid></item><item><title>Security Notice: Uncontrolled Resource Consumption with Highly-Compressed XMPP Stanzas</title><link>/2014/04/security-notice-uncontrolled-resource-consumption-with-highly-compressed-xmpp-stanzas</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The XMPP Standards Foundation has published a security notice describing an uncontrolled resource consumption vulnerability in several XMPP server implementations that support application-layer compression. Details can be found at &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/resources/security-notices/uncontrolled-resource-consumption-with-highly-compressed-xmpp-stanzas/"&gt;http://xmpp.org/resources/security-notices/uncontrolled-resource-consumption-with-highly-compressed-xmpp-stanzas/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2014 09:24:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-04-04:2014/04/security-notice-uncontrolled-resource-consumption-with-highly-compressed-xmpp-stanzas</guid></item><item><title>Third Security Test Day</title><link>/2014/03/third-security-test-day</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow sees the third security test day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Security test days help XMPP operators test-run with strong encryption settings prior to the big encryption switch-over scheduled for 19 May 2014.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A large number of XMPP sites have already signed up to the &lt;a href="https://github.com/stpeter/manifesto"&gt;ubiquitous encryption manifesto&lt;/a&gt;. More so, some of the participating sites have already permanently enabled strong encryption prior to the manifesto's go-live date!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the sites is Crypho. CTO Dr. Yiorgis Gozadinos explained his thinking in enabling strong encryption: “Everybody should have the right to privacy and confidentiality. Providing sane, strong encryption standards built-in in XMPP is a huge step to that direction."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ludost.net site admin Vasil Kolev has also been protecting his user's privacy: "Without strong encryption, these services become worse than useless - they become dangerous for the people that use them."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jabber.org, the original XMPP server on the Internet, is another site that has been playing an active role in the test days. As primary operator Peter Saint-Andre noted, "Although we've had the ability to encrypt the XMPP network for many years now, it's great to see strong momentum toward achieving that goal in the near future."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To join the growing number of sites that are enabling strong encryption:
​
1. Sign the &lt;a href="https://github.com/stpeter/manifesto"&gt;manifesto&lt;/a&gt; as an XMPP server admin or software developer. &lt;br /&gt;
2. Setup your site's encryption and check it at &lt;a href="https://xmpp.net/"&gt;XMPP.net&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;
3. Run with TLS encryption required on the 22nd of March and report issues in the &lt;a href="xmpp:operators@muc.xmpp.org?join"&gt;operators chatroom&lt;/a&gt; or on the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/operators"&gt;operators discussion list&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;br /&gt;
4. Spread the word about building secure federated communication!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2014 11:56:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-03-21:2014/03/third-security-test-day</guid></item><item><title>Second Security Test Day</title><link>/2014/02/second-security-test-day</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This Saturday (February 22, 2014), XMPP site operators are again flipping the "encrypt all traffic" switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second of four test days kicked off by the &lt;a href="https://github.com/stpeter/manifesto/blob/master/manifesto.txt"&gt;manifesto&lt;/a&gt; first published last fall. The aim is to encrypt all traffic between servers and clients on the public, federated XMPP network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can take part, too: ensure you have valid certificates on your server and that encryption is properly set up (see &lt;a href="http://wiki.xmpp.org/web/Securing_XMPP"&gt;http://wiki.xmpp.org/web/Securing_XMPP&lt;/a&gt; along with the documentation for your XMPP server software), then test your configuration using the tools at the &lt;a href="https://xmpp.net/"&gt;IM Observatory&lt;/a&gt; running at XMPP.net.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The manifesto team has managed to push the encryption level up to 12.5% of XMPP server-to-server traffic (see &lt;a href="https://xmpp.net/reports.php#starttls"&gt;https://xmpp.net/reports.php#starttls&lt;/a&gt;). The test days help to keep nudging this value up and to prepare for an "everything is encrypted...or else" day in May of this year (some operators have not flipped back to unencrypted traffic and are now running 100% encrypted servers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To join the team running the manifesto and thus help to secure the communications of XMPP users everywhere:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;test your server at the &lt;a href="https://xmpp.net/"&gt;IM Observatory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sign the manifesto at &lt;a href="https://github.com/stpeter/manifesto"&gt;https://github.com/stpeter/manifesto&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;chat with other XMPP operators in the &lt;a href="xmpp:operators@muc.xmpp.org?join"&gt;operators@muc.xmpp.org chatroom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;join the conversation on the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/operators"&gt;operators@xmpp.org email list&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's that easy!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2014 11:56:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2014-02-18:2014/02/second-security-test-day</guid></item><item><title>In-Band Real-Time Text to Draft Standard</title><link>/2013/10/in-band-real-time-text-to-draft-standard</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The XMPP Standards Foundation has advanced XEP-0301 (In-Band Real Time Text) from Experimental to Draft in its standards process. This technology enables "conversational text" to be exchanged instantly while it is being typed or created, which has applications in live speech transcription, systems for the deaf and hard of hearing, and other situations where speech is not practical.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 13:14:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2013-10-09:2013/10/in-band-real-time-text-to-draft-standard</guid></item><item><title>Stanza Forwarding to Draft Standard</title><link>/2013/10/stanza-forwarding-to-draft-standard</link><description>&lt;p&gt;XEP-0297, which defines a method for forwarding XMPP stanzas from one entity to another, has been advanced to a status of Draft within the XSF's standards process.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2013 12:51:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2013-10-09:2013/10/stanza-forwarding-to-draft-standard</guid></item><item><title>Server Dialback to Draft Standard</title><link>/2013/09/server-dialback-to-draft-standard</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The XMPP Standards Foundation has advanced the Server Dialback protocol specification (XEP-0220) to a status of Draft. Although this protocol was originally defined in RFC 3920, it was moved to XEP-0220 in 2007 when work began on the updated XMPP RFCs, and the documentation has been continually improved since then.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2013 03:33:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2013-09-28:2013/09/server-dialback-to-draft-standard</guid></item><item><title>Bidirectional Server-to-Server Connections</title><link>/2013/09/bidirectional-server-to-server-connections</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/about-xmpp/xsf/xmpp-council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; advanced &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0288.html"&gt;XEP-0288&lt;/a&gt; from Experimental to Draft in the XSF's standards process. This specification decreases the number of sockets necessary for server-to-server connections and also removes some of the practical barriers to connection multiplexing in the Server Dialback protocol.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2013 19:52:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2013-09-26:2013/09/bidirectional-server-to-server-connections</guid></item><item><title>Hackfest in Berlin on July 27</title><link>/2013/06/hackfest-in-berlin-on-july-27</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The XSF will hold a developer hackfest on July 27, 2013 in Berlin, Germany. This is the Saturday before &lt;a href="https://www.ietf.org/meeting/87/index.html"&gt;IETF 87&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details are available at &lt;a href="http://wiki.xmpp.org/web/Berlin_Hackfest"&gt;http://wiki.xmpp.org/web/Berlin_Hackfest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 11 Jun 2013 17:43:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2013-06-11:2013/06/hackfest-in-berlin-on-july-27</guid></item><item><title>The FOSDEM Schedule Is Set</title><link>/2013/01/the-fosdem-schedule-is-set</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The schedule for the Jabber/XMPP devroom at FOSDEM 2013 is now final. Visit https://fosdem.org/2013/schedule/track/jabber/ for the details and http://wiki.xmpp.org/web/FOSDEM_2013 for more information about our involvement with FOSDEM 2013.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2013 18:08:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2013-01-22:2013/01/the-fosdem-schedule-is-set</guid></item><item><title>XMPP Summit 13 in Brussels</title><link>/2012/12/xmpp-summit-13-in-brussels</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is just a quick note to inform you that the XSF will hold its 13th XMPP Summit in Brussels, Belgium on January 31 and February 1, 2013. This is Thursday and Friday before FOSDEM 2013. Details are on the wiki at http://wiki.xmpp.org/web/Summit_13 and join the summit@xmpp.org list to discuss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;edit: hmm, did I just edit this so it would reappear in folks feed readers... why yes, yes I did ;)&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 17 Dec 2012 12:06:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2012-12-17:2012/12/xmpp-summit-13-in-brussels</guid></item><item><title>Vulnerability in XMPP Server Dialback Implementations</title><link>/2012/08/vulnerability-in-xmpp-server-dialback-implementations</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Some implementations of the XMPP Server Dialback protocol have not been checking dialback responses to ensure that validated results are correlated with requests. Please see http://xmpp.org/resources/security-notices/server-dialback/ for detailed information about this important security notice.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 21 Aug 2012 11:10:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2012-08-21:2012/08/vulnerability-in-xmpp-server-dialback-implementations</guid></item><item><title>XMPP Summit</title><link>/2012/06/xmpp-summit</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We've decided to hold the next XMPP Summit in Portland, Oregon at the end of October. Mark your calendars for October 25th, which is the day after the &lt;a href="http://2012.krtconf.com/"&gt;Keeping it Realtime conference&lt;/a&gt;. Co-locating the XMPP Summit with krtconf makes a lot of sense, since both events are focused on building real-time applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many details are yet to be worked out (e.g., we might hold a two-day Summit instead of a one-day Summit), but we will post again in a few weeks once we know more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please note that krtconf is a small, high-caliber conference and will sell out quickly, so make sure to get on their email list and register early before all their tickets are sold out (and think about &lt;a href="http://blog.krtconf.com/post/24012727201/krtconf-2012-call-for-speakers"&gt;giving a talk&lt;/a&gt; at krtconf, too!).&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 15 Jun 2012 12:05:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2012-06-15:2012/06/xmpp-summit</guid></item><item><title>GSoC Coding Has Begun</title><link>/2012/06/gsoc-coding-has-begun</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href="/2012/04/and-our-gsoc-students-are/"&gt;Google Summer of Code students&lt;/a&gt; are merrily coding away now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Short descriptions of their projects can be found at &lt;a href="http://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/org/google/gsoc2012/xsf"&gt;google-melange.com&lt;/a&gt;, but for all the latest updates be sure to check out their blog posts, which are aggregated at &lt;a href="http://planet.jabber.org/"&gt;planet.jabber.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They make for fun reading!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 08 Jun 2012 11:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2012-06-08:2012/06/gsoc-coding-has-begun</guid></item><item><title>XMPP WG Session at IETF 83</title><link>/2012/03/xmpp-wg-session-at-ietf-83</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The IETF's XMPP Working Group will hold an in-person meeting this week at IETF 83 in Paris. The topics will include end-to-end encryption, server-to-server federation, and internationalization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remote access will also be accommodated. Here are the particulars:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Date&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Wednesday&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;March&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;28&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Time&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;15&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;16&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Central&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;European&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Time&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;14&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;UTC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Place&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Le&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Palais&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;des&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Congres&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;de&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Paris&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;France&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Chatroom&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;xmpp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;jabber&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;ietf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;org&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Audio&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Stream&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;http&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;://&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;ietf83streaming&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;dnsalias&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;net&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="sr"&gt;/ietf/i&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;etf837&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="na"&gt;m3u&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2012 18:57:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2012-03-26:2012/03/xmpp-wg-session-at-ietf-83</guid></item><item><title>Another Summer of Code</title><link>/2012/03/another-summer-of-code</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We're happy to announce that the XSF has been accepted to participate in the Google Summer of Code for 2012. See our &lt;a href="http://wiki.xmpp.org/web/Summer_of_Code_2012"&gt;wiki page&lt;/a&gt; for details. We still have time to add project ideas to the list there, so if you participate in an XMPP-related codebase feel free to get involved!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2012 10:46:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2012-03-21:2012/03/another-summer-of-code</guid></item><item><title>FOSDEM 2012 Report</title><link>/2012/03/fosdem-2012-report</link><description>&lt;p&gt;On February 3-6, the XSF and members of the XMPP community participated in both XMPP Summit 11 and FOSDEM 2012 in Brussels, Belgium. This is a late report about the activities there, based on the notes made at the time about the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/summit/2012-February/001084.html"&gt;Summit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/members/2012-February/006679.html"&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt; in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With regard to community outreach, we had a very successful presence at FOSDEM. In addition to the devroom, where we brought together a full afternoon of talks about XMPP and related topics, we also hosted a "real-time lounge" in one of the buildings on the ULB campus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Real-Time Lounge" src="/images/real-time-lounge.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, this approach was much more interactive than a table in a hallway: we held technology demonstrations, people were able to mingle more naturally and do some side-by-side coding, we showed a real-time microblogging feed on the wall, and we even patched in an encrypted video feed from the devroom using the Jitsi client. We also learned some valuable lessons about logistics and last-minute shopping at IKEA for things like tables and rugs. Let's hope the FOSDEM organizers allow us to repeat the experiment next year!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday and Monday we met at the Cisco office near the Brussels airport for technical discussions. The big focus this year was on finding better ways to integrate XMPP and the World Wide Web, from defining XMPP over WebSocket to using XMPP accounts as sources for authentication credentials in BrowserID. Various members of the XMPP community will be working on those initiatives in the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The FOSDEM weekend is always a lot of work to pull off, but it's worth it. Special thanks this year go to Florian Jensen of Flosoft for his local knowledge and assistance, to Dave Cridland and the rest of the Isode team for lugging those t-shirts and hoodies around, and to Jerome Paquay of Cisco for finding space for us to store all the stuff we bought at IKEA. See you next year, or at Summit 12 later this year in North America — stay tuned for details!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 12:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2012-03-14:2012/03/fosdem-2012-report</guid></item><item><title>Microsoft Adds XMPP Support to Windows Live APIs</title><link>/2011/09/microsoft-adds-xmpp-support-to-windows-live-apis</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has announced that it is adding support for XMPP to its Windows Live APIs, enabling any application or IM network to interoperate with Windows Live Messenger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Details are available at &lt;a href="http://www.liveside.net/2011/09/14/messenger-connect-is-now-live-connect-new-apis-for-skydrive-and-hotmail-calendar/"&gt;liveside.net&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://dev.live.com/"&gt;dev.live.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 14 Sep 2011 12:47:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-09-14:2011/09/microsoft-adds-xmpp-support-to-windows-live-apis</guid></item><item><title>Serving on the Board or Council</title><link>/2011/09/serving-on-the-board-or-council</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Each year the members of the XSF choose new people to provide technical leadership on the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/about-xmpp/xsf/xmpp-council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; and business leadership on the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/about-xmpp/xsf/the-xsf-board-of-directors/"&gt;XSF Board of Directors&lt;/a&gt;. These roles typically require only a few hours a week over the one-year term, and are a great way to get involved in the XMPP community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're interested in volunteering or know someone else who might be, visit the &lt;a href="http://wiki.xmpp.org/web/Board_and_Council_Elections_2011"&gt;wiki page&lt;/a&gt; or ask one of the current &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/about-xmpp/xsf/the-xsf-board-of-directors/"&gt;Board&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/about-xmpp/xsf/xmpp-council/"&gt;Council&lt;/a&gt; members for insights.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2011 21:45:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-09-13:2011/09/serving-on-the-board-or-council</guid></item><item><title>Skype Adds XMPP Support</title><link>/2011/06/skype-adds-xmpp-support</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Skype has &lt;a href="http://skypejournal.com/blog/2011/06/28/new-skype-beta-uses-im-interop-code/"&gt;added support for XMPP&lt;/a&gt; to its latest Windows beta, according to Phil Wolff of Skype Journal. Janko Roettgers provides &lt;a href="http://gigaom.com/2011/06/28/skype-xmpp-support/"&gt;further analysis&lt;/a&gt; at GigaOM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is yet another demonstration of the power of open standards.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2011 15:58:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-06-28:2011/06/skype-adds-xmpp-support</guid></item><item><title>Last Call on Jingle Audio Codecs</title><link>/2011/06/last-call-on-jingle-audio-codecs</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The XSF has issued a Last Call on &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0266.html"&gt;XEP-0262&lt;/a&gt;, which describes implementation considerations related to audio codecs for use in Jingle RTP sessions, and recommends PCMU and PCMA (G.711) as mandatory-to-implement technologies to provide a baseline for interoperability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have feedback, please post to the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/jingle"&gt;jingle@xmpp.org&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/standards"&gt;standards@xmpp.org&lt;/a&gt; discussion list before July 8, 2011.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2011 11:43:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-06-16:2011/06/last-call-on-jingle-audio-codecs</guid></item><item><title>Jingle ZRTP Spec Advances</title><link>/2011/06/jingle-zrtp-spec-advances</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier today, the XSF advanced &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0262.html"&gt;XEP-0262&lt;/a&gt; from Experimental to Draft in our standards process. This specification defines how to use &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6189"&gt;ZRTP&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0166.html"&gt;Jingle&lt;/a&gt; for end-to-end encryption of audio and video sessions, thus supplementing the existing SRTP method defined in &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0167.html"&gt;XEP-0167&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Special thanks to the &lt;a href="http://jitsi.org/"&gt;Jitsi&lt;/a&gt; team for providing implementation feedback.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jun 2011 23:24:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-06-15:2011/06/jingle-zrtp-spec-advances</guid></item><item><title>Progress on Internationalization</title><link>/2011/05/progress-on-internationalization</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As you might recall from our &lt;a href="/2011/02/brussels-trip-report/"&gt;Brussels trip report&lt;/a&gt; a few months ago, the XMPP community has a bit of work to do on internationalization. It's not that XMPP messages or addresses can't include non-ASCII characters, because we've had that capability since 1999. The problem comes from our dependence on a technology called stringprep (&lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc3454"&gt;RFC 3454&lt;/a&gt;), which we use to compare JabberIDs for tasks like authentication and authorization of users and servers. Because stringprep is being deprecated by the &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/"&gt;IETF&lt;/a&gt; for internationalized domain names, various application technologies that use stringprep for identifiers other than domain names (e.g., usernames and passwords) need to develop a new approach to comparing protocol strings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This subject was discussed extensively in the interim meeting of the IETF's XMPP Working Group in Brussels at the beginning February and in the PRECIS and XMPP sessions during IETF 80 in Prague at the end of March, resulting in some very rough consensus on a possible path forward. Today, yours truly submitted two Internet-Drafts that start to capture that rough consensus: a new &lt;a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-blanchet-precis-framework/"&gt;internationalization framework&lt;/a&gt; for consideration by the PRECIS Working Group and a &lt;a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-saintandre-xmpp-6122bis/"&gt;proposed replacement&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6122"&gt;RFC 6122&lt;/a&gt; for consideration by the XMPP Working Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Expect intensive work on these specifications over the next few months as we strive to modernize the internationalization support in XMPP.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 May 2011 22:20:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-05-17:2011/05/progress-on-internationalization</guid></item><item><title>Brussels Trip Report</title><link>/2011/02/brussels-trip-report</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Once again the XMPP community came together recently in Brussels to discuss XMPP technologies at the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/participate/the-xmpp-summit/xmpp-summit-10/"&gt;XMPP Summit&lt;/a&gt; and to evangelize at the &lt;a href="http://fosdem.org/"&gt;Free and Open Source Software Developers' European Meeting&lt;/a&gt; (FOSDEM). Here is a brief "trip report" from yours truly, XSF executive director Peter Saint-Andre.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weekend consisted of several related events: a "hackfest" on Friday at the Cisco offices outside Brussels, a "devroom" on Saturday afternoon at FOSDEM (held at a local university), an official XSF dinner on Sunday evening, and Monday it was back to the Cisco offices for the XMPP Summit in the morning and an interim meeting of the IETF's XMPP Working Group in the afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friday&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the hackfest on Friday, several XMPP software projects performed interoperability testing on &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0124.html"&gt;BOSH&lt;/a&gt; (the standard method for doing XMPP over HTTP). In addition, informal breakout groups discussed topics such as migrating to the IETF's upcoming vCard4 standard (it's time to say goodbye to our old &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0054.html"&gt;vcard-temp&lt;/a&gt; format!), multi-user Jingle and Jingle-based file sharing, and the need for an XMPP validation service at xmpp.org. Good progress was made on all of those topics (expect to see more about the validation effort over the next few months). After a classic developer's lunch of pizza and soft drinks, on Friday afternoon I presented a 90-minute tutorial on Unicode, UTF-8, stringprep, and other internationalization issues. Special thanks to everyone who paid attention the whole time! In addition, Klaas Wierenga of Cisco's Amsterdam office gave a talk about some experiments he and his team have conducted on single sign-on by combining XMPP's support for the Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL) with OpenID and the Security Assurance Markup Language (SAML).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, Friday night brought the legendary FOSDEM beer event, although some of us skipped out to catch up on email and such. However, we hear that a good time was had by all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/delirium.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saturday&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once again the good folks who run FOSDEM allotted a "developer room" to the Jabber/XMPP community, and once again it was packed most of the time. Especially popular were Remko Tronçon's intro to XMPP and the sessions on social networking and mobile applications. Dave Cridland of &lt;a href="http://www.isode.com/"&gt;Isode&lt;/a&gt; received extra points for his interactive presentation on security!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/devroom-summit10.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sunday&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year Sunday was a bit more ad-hoc than in years past because we did not have a table in the hallways at FOSDEM. However, that didn't stop folks from having productive hacking sessions and conversations on everything from ways to better evangelize XMPP within specialized developer communities, to improved handling of multiple simultaneous connected devices by clients and servers, to digital signatures and end-to-end encryption. Sunday evening also brought the now-traditional XSF dinner at &lt;a href="http://www.aubergebretonne.be/"&gt;L'Auberge Bretonne&lt;/a&gt; in Overijse outside Brussels. In addition to enjoying some of the best food and friendliest service you'll find anywhere, the assembled XMPP developers discussed a wide range of topics and might even have made progress on some technical issues! Many thanks to the companies and individuals who sponsored this year's dinner: &lt;a href="http://isode.com/"&gt;Isode&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://nokia.com/"&gt;Nokia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://andyet.net/"&gt;&amp;amp;yet&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://collabora.co.uk/"&gt;Collabora&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.ag-software.de/"&gt;AG Software&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.tigase.org/"&gt;Tigase&lt;/a&gt;,   &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/"&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://yate.null.ro/"&gt;Yate Project&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.tilanus.com/"&gt;Winfried Tilanus&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a href="http://helpim.org/"&gt;HelpIM&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.netinstall.cz/"&gt;Netinstall&lt;/a&gt;. Your support is very much appreciated!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/dinner-summit10.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monday&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Monday morning started with a demo of the entries in this year's developer challenge, sponsored by &lt;a href="http://www.nokia.com/"&gt;Nokia&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.mobilevikings.com/"&gt;Mobile Vikings&lt;/a&gt;. Although we didn't receive as many entries as last year, the winning entry showed creativity and the benefits of late-night hacking over the weekend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the excitement of the dev challenge, we held two technical sessions on Monday. In the morning, the XSF ran its XMPP Summit, with a focus on four topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reliable communications. Following up on implementation feedback provided by Matthew Wild of the &lt;a href="http://prosody.im/"&gt;Prosody project&lt;/a&gt;, Dave Cridland of &lt;a href="http://www.isode.com/"&gt;Isode&lt;/a&gt;, and Tobias Markmann of the &lt;a href="http://psi-im.org/"&gt;Psi project&lt;/a&gt;, the group discussed some improvements to our protocol for &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0198.html"&gt;stream management&lt;/a&gt;, with consensus to simplify the protocol in several ways. The &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/about-xmpp/xsf/the-xsf-council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; will be voting to approve those changes next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Transferring multiple files using Jingle. The still-experimental &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0234.html"&gt;Jingle extension for file transfer&lt;/a&gt; currently defines only a way to transfer a single file. After discussions in Brussels, we will be modifying the protocol to enable sending of multiple files (e.g., for photo-sharing applications). These modifications will occur over the next few months as we work to stabilize the relevant suite of specifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Distributed chatrooms. This is an early-stage research project to make &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0045.html"&gt;multi-user chat&lt;/a&gt; more robust and reliable, especially in deployments where server-to-server connectivity can be brittle. I provided an overview of the existing proposals (by myself, Carlo von Loesch and Philipp
Hancke of the &lt;a href="Carlo%20von%20Loesch,%20Philipp%20Hancke"&gt;psyced project&lt;/a&gt;, and XMPP Council member Kevin Smith of &lt;a href="http://www.isode.com/"&gt;Isode&lt;/a&gt;), and we had some agreement on technology direction and open issues. Now we just need to get to work on further defining the approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, Kurt Zeilenga of &lt;a href="http://www.isode.com/"&gt;Isode&lt;/a&gt; led a discussion about digital signatures and end-to-end encryption, reflecting the emerging consensus from discussions over the weekend among Joe Hildebrand and XMPP Council member Matt Miller of &lt;a href="http://www.cisco.com/"&gt;Cisco&lt;/a&gt;, Dave Cridland of &lt;a href="http://www.isode.com/"&gt;Isode&lt;/a&gt;, XMPP Council member Ralph Meijer of &lt;a href="http://www.mediamatic.nl/?lang=en"&gt;Mediamatic&lt;/a&gt;, and various other interested parties. This work is still somewhat preliminary, but those who've been involved have made good progress on issues like public key publishing (via &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0163.html"&gt;Personal Eventing Protocol&lt;/a&gt;) and message encryption (probably using an approach similar to the one that Matt Miller and I outlined in &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-miller-3923bis-02"&gt;draft-miller-3923bis&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/xmppwg-summit10.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Monday afternoon, the XSF ceded the floor to the IETF's &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/wg/xmpp/"&gt;XMPP Working Group&lt;/a&gt; so that the community could make progress on internationalization issues. Following up on my tutorial from Friday, I led a two-hour discussion to help narrow the scope of decisions that need to be made over the next few months as we work to replace stringprep with a more modern internationalization approach for XMPP. These are difficult issues, and solutions will require a bit of energy from the community this year, but hopefully we (along with other participants in the IETF's &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/wg/precis/"&gt;PRECIS WG&lt;/a&gt;) can develop an approach that is reasonable and sustainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final topic of the day centered around improved security and scalability for server-to-server federation, which is already one of the strong points of XMPP technologies. Given the rapid progress of &lt;a href="http://www.dnssec.net/"&gt;DNSSEC&lt;/a&gt; deployment over the last 12-18 months (including the imminent signing of the DNS root for .com domains), the group appeared to have agreement on pursuing an approach based on DNSSEC. Richard Barnes of &lt;a href="http://www.bbn.com/"&gt;BBN&lt;/a&gt;, Jonas Lindberg of &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/"&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;, and Joe Hildebrand of &lt;a href="http://www.cisco.com/"&gt;Cisco&lt;/a&gt; will be working on the relevant specifications soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a long weekend of technical work, the assembled developers scattered throughout Europe and the world, but not before many of them repaired to their favorite (but top-secret) ribs restaurant in the center of Brussels. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd like to give a special thanks to the helpful staff at the Cisco office in Diegem, Belgium (especially our local coordinator Catherine Piret) for hosting the Friday and Monday sessions, and of course to the volunteer organizers of FOSDEM for putting on yet another great conference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, be aware that plans are already afoot for XMPP Summit #11 in Portland, Oregon this summer. Expect announcements about that soon!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2011 16:38:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-02-18:2011/02/brussels-trip-report</guid></item><item><title>IETF Happenings</title><link>/2010/06/ietf-happenings</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Just over a year ago, the Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/xmpp/current/msg00000.html"&gt;approved formation&lt;/a&gt; of a new &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/wg/xmpp/"&gt;XMPP Working Group&lt;/a&gt; to work on revisions to the core XMPP specifications and related tasks. The first fruit of this initiative is a &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/xmpp/current/msg00740.html"&gt;working group last call&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-xmpp-3920bis/"&gt;draft-ietf-xmpp-3920bis&lt;/a&gt;, the core definition of XMPP. Officially this "WGLC" was two weeks long and therefore has already ended, but it will probably be extended for a week or two, so please review this (long!) specification and send your comments to the &lt;a href="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/xmpp"&gt;xmpp@ietf.org&lt;/a&gt; discussion list as soon as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the working group last call is complete and all feedback has been incorporated, the responsible area director at the IETF will issue an IETF-wide last call for additional comments. After that the document will go before the &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/iesg/"&gt;Internet Engineering Steering Group&lt;/a&gt; (IESG) for a vote. You'll notice that the author of this document (c'est moi) is also an &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/iesg/bio/peter-saint-andre.html"&gt;IESG member&lt;/a&gt;, so I'll be recusing myself from the IESG vote, which should occur sometime over the summer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next month or so, we'll start the same process with &lt;a href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/doc/draft-ietf-xmpp-3921bis/"&gt;draft-ietf-xmpp-3921bis&lt;/a&gt;, which defines how to use XMPP for messaging, contact lists, presence, and other core IM features.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once 3920bis and 3921bis are complete, the XMPP WG will move on to end-to-end security and other fascinating topics, so join the xmpp@ietf.org discussion list for all the fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;--Peter Saint-Andre&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2010 12:04:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-06-01:2010/06/ietf-happenings</guid></item><item><title>Issue Tracker</title><link>/2010/02/issue-tracker</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The XSF's &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/xsf/teams/infrastructure/"&gt;Infrastructure Team&lt;/a&gt; has installed an issue tracker for use by the XMPP Standards Foundation. Because the core work of the XSF is the development of protocol specifications, we will use the "Spec Issues" project in the issue tracker to keep track of bug reports and feature requests related to our core &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/"&gt;specification series&lt;/a&gt; (XEPs) and related documentation such as &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/schemas/"&gt;XML schemas&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/registrar/"&gt;data registries&lt;/a&gt;. Anyone can submit issues for consideration, and those tickets will be handled by the XSF's &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/xsf/teams/techreview/"&gt;Technical Review Team&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/editor.shtml"&gt;XEP Editor&lt;/a&gt;, and other responsible parties (we're still working out the details about how we will track this feedback and incorporate it into our specifications).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to help out, the first step is to &lt;a href="http://tracker.xmpp.org/"&gt;create an account&lt;/a&gt;, then you can start to submit bug reports and feature requests at the &lt;a href="http://tracker.xmpp.org/browse/SPEC"&gt;spec issues project&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue tracker is just the first in a series of process improvements we are working on to make the XSF's standards even more transparent and efficient. Stay tuned for further reports in the near future!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-- Peter Saint-Andre&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2010 13:05:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-02-25:2010/02/issue-tracker</guid></item><item><title>Welcome, Facebook!</title><link>/2010/02/welcome-facebook</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Earlier today a member of the XMPP developer community noticed that he could log into Facebook chat &lt;a href="http://www.deepdarc.com/2010/02/10/facebook-turns-on-xmpp-support/"&gt;using a standard XMPP client&lt;/a&gt;. The news has since been &lt;a href="http://blog.facebook.com/blog.php?post=297991732130"&gt;confirmed by Facebook&lt;/a&gt;. This is great news for XMPP, and great news for open standards in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although Facebook has not yet enabled federation with the rest of the public XMPP network, I'd imagine it is only a matter of time until that happens (after all, Google Talk launched in August 2005 but didn't federate until early 2006). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, it seems that we'll need to seriously increase our informal estimates about the number of XMPP users. By about 400 million. :)
--stpeter&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2010 13:28:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-02-10:2010/02/welcome-facebook</guid></item><item><title>FOSDEM and Summit Report</title><link>/2010/02/fosdem-and-summit-report</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The XSF held another successful &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/summit/summit8.shtml"&gt;XMPP Summit&lt;/a&gt; over the weekend at &lt;a href="http://fosdem.org/2010/"&gt;FOSDEM 2010&lt;/a&gt; in Brussels, Belgium. Many thanks to the companies who sponsored this event: &lt;a href="http://www.nokia.com/"&gt;Nokia&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.vodafone.com"&gt;Vodafone&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://collabora.co.uk/"&gt;Collabora&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.isode.com/"&gt;Isode&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.tandberg.com/"&gt;TANDBERG&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.buddycloud.com/"&gt;Buddycloud&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://collecta.com/"&gt;Collecta&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.ooros.com/"&gt;Ooros&lt;/a&gt;. Special thanks to Nokia for temporarily donating some N900 devices for the Developer Challenge, and to &lt;a href="http://mobilevikings.com/"&gt;Mobile Vikings&lt;/a&gt; for the SIM cards that enabled a number of XMPP developers to experiment with building mobile applications at the conference. And extra special thanks to XSF Board member Florian Jensen for his hard work on local coordination (as well as the photos in this blog post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The weekend events started with a "hackfest" on Friday where developers could work together on code projects, perform interoperability testing, and give informal talks on technical topics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Saturday we had a "devroom" at FOSDEM 2010, which was packed the entire afternoon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/summit8-devroom.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most popular sessions was "Stump the XMPP Experts" with XMPP book authors and the current &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; (left to right, the experts were Kevin Smith, Ralph Meijer, Remko Tronçon, Matthew Wild, Jack Moffitt, Dave Cridland, and Peter Saint-Andre).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/summit8-stump.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The talks ranged from fun demos to technical explorations of XMPP technologies. Here Ralph Meijer illustrates the use of Atom feeds over XMPP pubsub (photo by Dan Brickley).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/summit8-ralphm.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other speakers included the winners of the XMPP developer challenge, Frank Scholz and Philippe Normand, who gave a talk about their &lt;a href="http://coherence.beebits.net/wiki/MirabeauHowTo"&gt;Mirabeau&lt;/a&gt; application for personal media networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/summit8-mirabeau.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On both Saturday and Sunday the XSF had a booth at FOSDEM, which was the center of many ad-hoc discussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/summit8-booth.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a new T-shirt design especially for the event, here donned along with an older Jabber shirt and last year's XMPP design by Sebastiaan Deckers of the Pandion project, Joe Hildebrand of Cisco, XSF Board member Florian Jensen, and XMPP Council member Ralph Meijer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/summit8-shirts.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual, one of the highlights of the weekend was the official XSF dinner, where participants got a chance to know each other better over some excellent Belgian food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" src="/images/summit8-dinner.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, on Monday we held the Summit itself, with in-depth discussions and brainstorming sessions about technical challenges facing the XMPP developer community. The hot topics this year included:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mobile Optimizations. Here there was general agreement that we need to experiment further with some of the technologies we defined at past Summits (including &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0237.html"&gt;Roster Versioning&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0273.html"&gt;SIFT&lt;/a&gt;), more fully specify methods for session resumption and quick reconnect, and perhaps define a straightforward method for "hushing" a session to turn off incoming presence notifications. Expect follow-up discussion on the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/mobile"&gt;mobile@xmpp.org list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Network Reliability. Here again the participants concluded that we need more implementation and deployment experience with existing extensions, especially &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0198.html"&gt;stanza acknowledgements&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0184.html"&gt;message receipts&lt;/a&gt;, so that we can see what reliability gaps remain once those are more widely deployed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Server-to-Server Security. We had a wide-ranging discussion about &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-xmpp-dna-00"&gt;Domain Name Assertions&lt;/a&gt;, a proposal being worked on within the IETF's XMPP Working Group that would enable XMPP hosting services to deploy SSL/TLS without having access to the private keys for the domains they host. One result of the discussion was agreement to further explore attribute certificates as the most secure method for this feature. Another was to probably define a new DNS SRV record for delegated services; for example, _xmpp-delegate._tcp.example.com might point to google.com, dreamhost.com, gmx.com, cisco.com, i-pobox.net, or some other hosting provider so that a connecting user or server would know that it's OK to connect to the hosting provider securely. These topics will be discussed on the &lt;a href="https://www.ietf.org/mailman/listinfo/xmpp"&gt;xmpp@ietf.org list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jingle. There was quite a bit of excitement about Thiago Camargo's proposal for &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/inbox/jingle-nodes.html"&gt;Jingle Relay Nodes&lt;/a&gt;, which will make it easier to realistically deploy Jingle services for voice, video, and other multimedia use cases. Sign up for the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/jingle"&gt;jingle@xmpp.org list&lt;/a&gt; to discuss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Multi-User Chat ("MUC"). Although this is one of the oldest and most widely-used XMPP extensions (powering everything from IETF chatrooms to replacements for IRC in military applications), further improvements are on the way. Summit participants discussed a more flexible model for user roles (provisionally called "hats"), the ability to share and subscribe metadata about the room and its occupants, the use of MUC as a control channel for voice and video conferences (i.e., &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0272.html"&gt;Multiparty Jingle&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/inbox/distributedmuc.html"&gt;distribution of MUC rooms&lt;/a&gt; across servers, and several other topics. We're sure to have much discussion about these topics over the weeks and months ahead on the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/muc"&gt;muc@xmpp.org&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/standards"&gt;standards@xmpp.org&lt;/a&gt; lists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As in years past, it was extremely beneficial to gather active members of the XMPP developer community together for coding, outreach, and in-depth technical discussion. The success of this year's Summit is already inspiring developers to work on smaller-scale events around the world, and to plan for XMPP Summit #9 in North America this summer. Stay tuned for details.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;--stpeter&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 10 Feb 2010 12:28:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-02-10:2010/02/fosdem-and-summit-report</guid></item><item><title>CA Updates</title><link>/2009/09/ca-updates</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Since 2006 the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/"&gt;XMPP Standards Foundation&lt;/a&gt; has been &lt;a href="http://blog.xmpp.org/index.php/2007/02/practical-network-security/"&gt;offering free digital certificates&lt;/a&gt; to administrators of XMPP servers as a way of encouraging encryption of point-to-point "hops" on the XMPP network. This program has been successful in several ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thousands of XMPP deployments currently use certificates issued by the &lt;a href="https://xmpp.net/"&gt;XMPP ICA&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Popular XMPP clients and servers have fixed bugs in their code related to certificate handling.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The XMPP community has gained practical experience with stronger encryption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since the beginning, the XSF has functioned as an "intermediate certification authority" or "ICA", where the root CA is &lt;a href="http://www.startssl.com/"&gt;StartCom&lt;/a&gt;. In collaboration with our friends at StartCom, we recently decided that StartCom will directly offer Class 1 certificates through its normal process at &lt;a href="http://www.startssl.com/"&gt;http://www.startssl.com/&lt;/a&gt; instead of running a specialized service only for XMPP servers at xmpp.net. This lowers the administrative burden both for the XSF (we will no longer need to manually approve certain certificate requests) and for StartCom (they will be able to use the same code for issuing both web server certificates and IM server certificates).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have always seen our arrangement with StartCom as something of an experiment. Although there were many good reasons for choosing StartCom as our partner in offering free certificates (they enabled us to run an intermediate CA, they have great customer service, and the price was extremely competitive), that partnership was never exclusive. We have hoped that StartCom's example would encourage other CAs to offer XMPP-specific certificates as well. Although that has not happened yet, modifying our relationship with StartCom is a movement in that direction because their issuance of XMPP-specific certificates is now part of their "mainstream" offerings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The XSF will continue to issue and honor certificates via the XMPP ICA for a few more months, but StartCom is hard at work on upgrading their core service to directly offer XMPP certificates at their own site, so expect a switchover sometime in the relatively near future. We will keep you up to date at this blog and at xmpp.net regarding any service issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we would like to thank &lt;a href="https://blog.startcom.org/"&gt;Eddy Nigg&lt;/a&gt; and his team at StartCom for all their hard work over the years. They are true security professionals and a pleasure to work with. We certainly hope that our paths cross again in the future.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2009 14:35:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2009-09-08:2009/09/ca-updates</guid></item><item><title>Board and Council Elections</title><link>/2009/09/board-and-council-elections</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Once a year, the XMPP Standards Foundation holds elections for its &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/xsf/board/"&gt;Board of Directors&lt;/a&gt; and for the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt;. That time is now, so the XSF is actively soliciting people to stand for election. Here is the division of responsibilities between the two groups:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Board provides business leadership for the XSF by handling things like fundraising, contracts, grants, legal issues, planning the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/summit/"&gt;XMPP Summit&lt;/a&gt; meetings, and choosing volunteers for various official posts such as the Secretary and Executive Director. Those who serve on the Board are &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; required to be &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/xsf/members/"&gt;elected members&lt;/a&gt; of the XSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Council provides technical leadership for the XSF by managing the XSF's &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0001.html"&gt;standards process&lt;/a&gt;, deciding which &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/inbox/"&gt;proposals&lt;/a&gt; to accept as &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/"&gt;official XEPs&lt;/a&gt;, voting on advancement of XEPs through the process from Experimental to Draft to Final, and providing oversight for the functions of the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/editor.shtml"&gt;XMPP Extensions Editor&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0053.html"&gt;XMPP Registrar&lt;/a&gt;. Those who serve on the XMPP Council are required to be elected members of the XSF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in standing for election, please visit &lt;a href="http://wiki.xmpp.org/web/Board_and_Council_Elections_2009"&gt;http://wiki.xmpp.org/web/Board_and_Council_Elections_2009&lt;/a&gt; and create a page about your candidacy by the close of business on Friday, September 11, 2009.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 01 Sep 2009 11:58:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2009-09-01:2009/09/board-and-council-elections</guid></item><item><title>XMPP.org and Jabber.org: Rough Consensus and Running Code</title><link>/2009/04/xmpporg-and-jabberorg-rough-consensus-and-running-code</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It's well-known that XMPP technologies emerged from the open-source server project first released by Jeremie Miller in 1999, as well as the combined software/operator community that grew up around the server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the early days, "Jabber" meant many things: Jer's server, the protocol used between clients and servers, the server network, the community in general, even a company called Jabber.com (then Jabber Inc., purchased by Cisco Systems in late 2008). Over time we have worked to disambiguate the terms. Thus Jer's server was renamed jabberd and the protocol was renamed XMPP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, the relationship between the jabber.org and xmpp.org domains has remained a bit nebulous. Several years ago, the Board of Directors of the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/xsf/"&gt;XMPP Standards Foundation&lt;/a&gt; clarified the matter by stating that the jabber.org domain was a community effort hosted on XSF machines but operationally independent of the XSF. That clarification was never formally announced, but the decision was recently re-affirmed by the current Board so now seems like an appropriate time to make the distinction more public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The basic division of responsibilities is this: the XSF focuses on the "rough consensus" part of "rough consensus and running code" by defining the core protocols used by the entire XMPP community, as published at the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/"&gt;xmpp.org website&lt;/a&gt;; by contrast, the Jabber.org team focuses on the "running code" part by offering a popular, XMPP-based, real-time communications service. This focus was incorporated into the recent redesign of the &lt;a href="http://www.jabber.org/"&gt;jabber.org website&lt;/a&gt; (which now is dedicated to information about the jabber.org IM service), and has long been evident at the xmpp.org website as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now you know!
--stpeter&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2009 09:43:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2009-04-30:2009/04/xmpporg-and-jabberorg-rough-consensus-and-running-code</guid></item><item><title>MXM #2</title><link>/2009/04/mxm-2</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Reported by Peter Saint-Andre&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Back in March, we decided to hold an informal "Monthly XMPP Meeting" among developers in our community. Here is a brief report on the second such meeting, held today (April 14) in the &lt;a href="xmpp:jdev@conference.jabber.org?join"&gt;jdev@conference.jabber.org&lt;/a&gt; chatroom (the archived discussion log is &lt;a href="http://logs.jabber.org/jdev@conference.jabber.org/2009-04-14.html#14:06:45"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the topics we discussed...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last Call for &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0232.html"&gt;XEP-0232: Software Information&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The points raised included:
-   Is this a misuse of service discovery?
-   Will this make &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0115.html"&gt;entity capability&lt;/a&gt; caches less useful because they will be too large to search easily?
-   Does it make more sense to publish this information via the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0163.html"&gt;Personal Eventing Protocol&lt;/a&gt; using the old &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0092.html"&gt;software version&lt;/a&gt; format?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; will vote on XEP-0232 at its next meeting (April 22). More feedback is welcome before then on the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/standards"&gt;standards@xmpp.org&lt;/a&gt; mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last Call for &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0237.html"&gt;XEP-0237: Roster Versioning&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is general agreement that this proposed modification to the core XMPP roster management protocol is in good shape. There are still a few edge cases to figure out, especially the empty roster case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last Calls for the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/tech/jingle.shtml"&gt;core Jingle specs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No real discussion here. Most people seemed to think that these are ready for advancement to Draft in the XSF's standard process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pubsub/PEP implementations Consensus that we need more interop testing among implementation such as ejabberd, idavoll, Openfire, and Tigase. Perhaps we will make this a focus at the next &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/summit/"&gt;XMPP Summit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0198.html"&gt;XEP-0198: Stream Management&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People like this because it will improve the reliability of communications across the network. Now we need to go forth and implement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bidirectional server-to-server connections&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As defined in RFC 3920, XMPP requires two TCP connections for each server-to-server ("s2s") link. This is sub-optimal. We decided that we need to hold a dedicated discussion session about s2s fixes and improvements (server dialback, multiplexing domains over a given stream, etc.). We agreed to make that the focus of the next Monthly XMPP Meeting, tentatively scheduled for May 5 (add it to your calendar &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/xsf/XSF.ics"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My impression is that it is quite valuable to hold these meetings. I especially found it helpful to have a more general community discussion about XMPP Extension Protocols that are currently in Last Call or under heavy development, because it gives people a chance to talk about them in real time rather than only on the standards@xmpp.org mailing list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So expect us to keep holding this kind of online meeting over the coming months.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 14 Apr 2009 15:38:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2009-04-14:2009/04/mxm-2</guid></item><item><title>Google Summer of Code</title><link>/2009/02/google-summer-of-code</link><description>&lt;p&gt;At its meeting yesterday, the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; decided not to participate in the &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/"&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; (GSoC) for 2009. There are several reasons for this decision:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many of the longtime open-source projects in the XMPP community are quite mature but lacking in obvious mentors or even an open architecture of participation. On the other hand, there are many vibrant new projects in the community but they are not quite mature enough yet to provide a stable environment for student contributors. Together these two factors mean that we would not be able to provide a suitably nurturing environment for introducing GSoC students to the ways of open source software development, which is the primary goal of the program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Although the XMPP community has benefited from its participation in GSoC 2005-2008, it might be fair to let other open-source communities have a chance to take part rather than hogging resources during a year when we think we wouldn't be able to take full advantage of the program.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GSoC is very rewarding but it is a lot of work for the mentors and the organization admin (c'est moi), and the Council members felt it would be inefficient to spend a great deal of time and energy on the program this year given the considerations cited above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, we hope to have the chance to participate again in 2010 so that we can continue on the path to world domination for XMPP technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;--Peter Saint-Andre&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Feb 2009 20:33:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2009-02-26:2009/02/google-summer-of-code</guid></item><item><title>XMPP Roundup #7: Brussels Report</title><link>/2009/02/xmpp-roundup-7-brussels-report</link><description>&lt;p&gt;[Reporter: Peter Saint-Andre]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before the memories of &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/summit/summit6.shtml"&gt;XMPP Summit 6&lt;/a&gt; fade away, I wanted to provide a brief report on the latest and greatest of our "IRL" (in real life) meetings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We held the first XMPP Summit in the summer of 2005 to perform server interop testing and discuss topics of interest. Thirteen developers showed up and we made good progress on a number of issues, including the pubsub simplifications now known as &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0163.html"&gt;Personal Eventing Protocol&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to 2009 for the sixth summit, where over 40 developers participated -- so many that we needed to split up into smaller discussion groups to complete some serious work. During the official XMPP Summit day (Monday the 9th) we had formal or informal break-out groups about &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/mobile/2009-February/000061.html"&gt;mobile optimizations&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/bosh/2009-February/000146.html"&gt;BOSH&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/pubsub/2009-February/000086.html"&gt;pubsub&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/operators/2009-February/000390.html"&gt;operational challenges&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/jingle/2009-February/000542.html"&gt;Jingle&lt;/a&gt;, security, and several other topics. As a result we came up with clear action items to work on regarding a number of XMPP technologies, some of which have already been completed and others of which are underway. Expect the remaining items to be mostly finished in the next few weeks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one-day XMPP Summit was not the only activity in Brussels. We got started on Friday the 6th with a "Jingle Thingle", which was similar in format to the very first Summit by including both interop testing and discussion. Voice and video calls were completed and we talked about the use of Jingle for both file transfer and end-to-end encryption, resulting in Jingle "profiles" of both &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0260.html"&gt;SOCKS5 Bytestreams&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0261.html"&gt;In-Band Bytestreams&lt;/a&gt; as well as a promising proposal for &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-meyer-xmpp-e2e-encryption-00.html"&gt;encryption&lt;/a&gt; of XMPP traffic. This event helped us get much closer to stabilizing Jingle and advancing the core specifications to a status of Draft in our standards process, which should happen in the very near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saturday the 7th and Sunday the 8th were outreach days at &lt;a href="http://fosdem.org/"&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt;, one of the largest open-source conferences in Europe. On Saturday the XMPP community had a "devroom" from 1 PM to 7 PM, where we presented numerous talks and tutorials about XMPP technologies (thanks to everyone who volunteered to speak). The room held 75 people but it was overflowing almost the entire time! On both Saturday and Sunday we also had a hallway stand where we spread the word and sold out of our first-ever batch of XMPP T-shirts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Keeping with tradition, on Sunday evening we held an XMPP dinner so that developers could get to know each other on a more personal level. At Summits past the XMPP Standards Foundation has paid for the dinner, but this year we took a more flexible approach by asking individuals and companies to chip in toward the cost. Many thanks to Nokia, Isode, StanzIQ, bluendo, AG-Software, Flosoft.biz, Thomas Koeppen, and several other individuals for helping to defray the costs. Special thanks go out to Florian Jensen of Flosoft.biz for acting as our "man on the ground" in Brussels to help coordinate with the restaurant as well as the hotel where we held the Jingle Thingle and XMPP Summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our in-person conferences continue to grow in popularity and we're already looking forward to XMPP Summit 7 in North America this summer (exact dates and location yet to be announced). The energy in the XMPP community is palpable, so expect more good things in the months ahead as our work in Brussels bears fruit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onward and upward!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 25 Feb 2009 21:44:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2009-02-25:2009/02/xmpp-roundup-7-brussels-report</guid></item><item><title>Privacy Policy Approved</title><link>/2008/12/privacy-policy-approved</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In its meeting today, the XSF's &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/xsf/board/"&gt;Board of Directors&lt;/a&gt; approved the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/xsf/privacy.shtml"&gt;privacy policy&lt;/a&gt; for xmpp.org and jabber.org, including the &lt;a href="http://www.jabber.org/web/Jabber.org"&gt;jabber.org IM service&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many thanks to everyone who provided feedback on the draft policy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2008 14:30:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2008-12-09:2008/12/privacy-policy-approved</guid></item><item><title>Draft Privacy and Security Policy</title><link>/2008/10/draft-privacy-and-security-policy</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Among other things, the XSF runs the jabber.org IM service, which is one of the largest nodes on the open XMPP network (yes, we really do believe in running code!). However, we've never had a privacy and security policy for this service. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently we've been working to define such a policy so that folks who use the service know exactly where they stand. A draft of the policy is located at &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/xsf/privacy.shtml"&gt;http://xmpp.org/xsf/privacy.shtml&lt;/a&gt; and your feedback is welcome. Before the end of the year, the &lt;a href="http://xmpp.org/xsf/board/"&gt;XSF Board of Directors&lt;/a&gt; will vote to approve the policy, but we are seeking input well before then so that all concerns are addressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To send us your thoughts, feel free to comment here or to use the contact methods specified in the policy. Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2008 19:52:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2008-10-20:2008/10/draft-privacy-and-security-policy</guid></item><item><title>IM Service Migration</title><link>/2008/05/im-service-migration</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Here at the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/"&gt;XMPP Standards Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, we're not just a bunch of protocol geeks. As firm believers in the old IETF mantra of "rough consensus and running code", we run one of the most central nodes on the XMPP network: the jabber.org IM service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of care and attention goes into running this service: hardware, hosting, software, and precious time donated by a dedicated group of volunteers. All of those factors were in evidence during our just-completed migration of the service to a new machine. Special thanks are due to the following companies and individuals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.hp.com/"&gt;HP&lt;/a&gt; donated a powerful new machine that will be dedicated to providing this service. Paul Holland, Kartik Subbarao, and Dann Frazier deserve particular recognition for their
assistance.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jerry Pasker of &lt;a href="http://usshc.com/"&gt;United States Secure Hosting Center&lt;/a&gt; once again went above and beyond the call
of duty regarding physical hosting and support services. Thanks also to Jer, Jason, and Seth for getting the machine installed and configured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.ejabberd.im/"&gt;ejabberd project&lt;/a&gt; builds the software that we run for this service. The good folks at
&lt;a href="http://www.process-one.net/"&gt;Process-one&lt;/a&gt;, especially Mickaël Rémond, provided invaluable assistance with bug fixes and real-time support.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our dedicated team of infrastructure volunteers put in lots of time, often at odd hours, to make this migration a reality. We could not have done it without work by Jonathan Siegle, Florian Jensen, Kevin Smith, Dave Cridland, Matthew Wild, Jack Moffitt, Alexander Gnauck, Niek Bergman, and others (you know who you are!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have migrated the jabber.org service to a new machine, we look forward to rolling out some new features that were not possible on our old machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for details...&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 22 May 2008 15:51:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2008-05-22:2008/05/im-service-migration</guid></item><item><title>Google Summer of Code 2008</title><link>/2008/04/google-summer-of-code-2008</link><description>&lt;p&gt;For the fourth year in a row, the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/"&gt;XMPP Standards Foundation&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/2008/xmpp/about.html"&gt;participating&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/2008/"&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt;. Our projects for 2008 are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mateusz Biliński (&lt;a href="http://blog.bilinski.it/"&gt;vArDo&lt;/a&gt;) -- &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/2008/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=4DBB14A9D1CA8C7C"&gt;Plug-in system for Gajim&lt;/a&gt; (Mentor: Yann LeBoulanger)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adam Czachorowski (&lt;a href="http://gislan.utumno.pl/"&gt;gislan&lt;/a&gt;) -- &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/2008/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=CC0FB57C68942C8C"&gt;Metacontacts support and various roster improvements for Psi&lt;/a&gt; (Mentor: Remko Tronçon)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tomas Karasek (&lt;a href="http://tomk-soc08.blogspot.com/"&gt;tomk&lt;/a&gt;) -- &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/2008/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=8808F80FD61017BF"&gt;Bidirectional-streams Over Synchronous HTTP (XEP-0124) support in Gajim Jabber client&lt;/a&gt; (Mentor: Yann LeBoulanger)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aleksey Palazchenko (&lt;a href="http://alek.silverstone.name/en/tags/soc"&gt;AlekSi&lt;/a&gt;) -- &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/2008/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=3B03DDE3FDEE3312"&gt;Psi: Message history&lt;/a&gt; (Mentor: Kevin Smith)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Safa Sofuoğlu (&lt;a href="http://gsoc.safasofuoglu.org/"&gt;huni&lt;/a&gt;) -- &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/2008/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=925383C386048A54"&gt;Updating and Improving BOSH Support of Openfire&lt;/a&gt; (Mentor: Gaston Dombiak)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paweł Wiejacha (&lt;a href="http://senu.rootnode.net/blog/index.php?/categories/1-gsoc"&gt;senu&lt;/a&gt;) -- &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/2008/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=2E3332B677411001"&gt;Themable WebKit-based Chat Dialogs&lt;/a&gt; (Mentor: Kevin Smith)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's to another successful summer of coding!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 21 Apr 2008 12:39:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2008-04-21:2008/04/google-summer-of-code-2008</guid></item><item><title>Annual Report</title><link>/2008/03/annual-report</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Regrettably, the XSF has not issued an annual report since 2002. It seems we're always too busy getting things done to report on our activities. But this year we decided to turn over a new leaf by completing an annual report, available at &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/docs/annual-report-2007.shtml"&gt;http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/docs/annual-report-2007.shtml&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feedback is welcome, as always.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2008 19:16:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2008-03-18:2008/03/annual-report</guid></item><item><title>The Host With the Most</title><link>/2008/02/the-host-with-the-most</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/"&gt;XMPP Standards Foundation&lt;/a&gt; is happy to finally recognize &lt;a href="http://usshc.com"&gt;United States Secure Hosting Center&lt;/a&gt; as an in-kind &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/sponsors/usshc.shtml"&gt;sponsor&lt;/a&gt; of the XSF. USSHC has been hosting the XSF's server infrastructure (and before that the jabber.org project's machines) for as long as anyone can remember, and has unfailingly provided not only a secure location for our infrastructure but also extremely reliable service. After many years of laboring in obscurity, USSHC is finally receiving due recognition for its efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We look forward to continuing our relationship with USSHC for many years to come!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2008 11:46:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2008-02-20:2008/02/the-host-with-the-most</guid></item><item><title>More Freedom</title><link>/2008/01/more-freedom</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Several months ago a developer in the Jabber/XMPP community let us know that the XSF's intellectual property rights policy prevented him from including text, examples, and schemas from our &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/"&gt;XEP&lt;/a&gt; specifications in his code. In particular, the &lt;a href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"&gt;Creative Commons Attribution License&lt;/a&gt; (which we were using to cover XEPs) is not consistent with the &lt;a href="http://www.debian.org/social_contract#guidelines"&gt;Debian Free Software Guidelines&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we are big fans of Debian GNU/Linux around here (we use it to run all the jabber.org/xmpp.org infrastructure), we decided to investigate the matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After some research as well as discussion by the XSF Board of Directors, the XSF membership, and the debian-legal mailing list, we settled on a slightly-modified &lt;a href="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/mit-license.php"&gt;MIT license&lt;/a&gt; to cover our specifications. (No, we didn't want to use a modified license, but we needed to make certain rights crystal-clear to those who develop XMPP-based software and deploy XMPP-based services.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This license gives folks even more freedom to implement, deploy, copy, modify, merge, publish, translate, distribute, sublicense, even sell copies of our specifications. And since Jabber technologies have always been focused on freedom, it's only appropriate that the XSF's specifications should be as free as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The updated license is here:&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/ipr-policy.shtml"&gt;http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/ipr-policy.shtml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 31 Jan 2008 13:26:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2008-01-31:2008/01/more-freedom</guid></item><item><title>Jingle Update</title><link>/2008/01/jingle-update</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We &lt;a href="http://blog.xmpp.org/?p=32"&gt;issued a Last Call&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0166.html"&gt;Jingle&lt;/a&gt; specifications on November 21st. So why have they not yet advanced to a status of &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0001.html#states-Draft"&gt;Draft&lt;/a&gt; within the XSF's &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0001.html"&gt;standards process&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The end-of-year holidays intervened.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are gathering detailed feedback from a wide variety of implementors, including Google Talk, Nokia, Asterisk, and the One Laptop Per Child Project (via &lt;a href="http://www.collabora.co.uk/"&gt;Collabora&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are defining a &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-sip-xmpp-media-00.html"&gt;thorough mapping&lt;/a&gt;between Jingle and SIP for multimedia session negotiation, and still need to define the mapping in the direction from SIP to Jingle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We are working on some specifications that describe how to use Jingle as the method for negotiating additional session types (for example, file transfer and whiteboarding) so we can make sure that Jingle semantics are reusable for applications other than voice and video.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These efforts should be finished in the next few weeks, which will enable the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; to vote on advancing the Jingle specifications during its in-person meeting at the &lt;a href="http://blog.xmpp.org/?p=33"&gt;XMPP devcon&lt;/a&gt; in Brussels on February 24-25.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2008 10:51:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2008-01-28:2008/01/jingle-update</guid></item><item><title>DevCon #4</title><link>/2008/01/devcon-4</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.fosdem.org/2008/"&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt; is coming up soon (Brussels, February 23-24) and the XSF will once again hold a &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/devcon/devcon4.shtml"&gt;devcon&lt;/a&gt; (on February 24 and 25).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/"&gt;XMPP Standards Foundation&lt;/a&gt; would like to encourage XMPP technologists from Europe and beyond to participate, especially in the devcon. In its meeting earlier this week, the XSF Board of Directors authorized a new policy: the Foundation will pay the hotel costs of any XSF member who participates in the devcon. The XSF may ask that you share a room with another XSF member, but we will pay for up to four nights' stay at the Atlas hotel in the center of Brussels (where we will be staying and meeting).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To take advantage of this offer, you must participate in the devcon and you must be an XSF member. If you are not yet an XSF member or you need to renew your membership, you can do so &lt;a href="http://wiki.jabber.org/index.php/Membership_Applications_January_2008"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; until January 20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we need to tell the hotel how many rooms we need, please contact XSF Executive Director Peter Saint-Andre or XSF Chair Alexander Gnauck by Friday, January 18 if you would like to take advantage of this offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you in Brussels!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jan 2008 11:46:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2008-01-10:2008/01/devcon-4</guid></item><item><title>Jingle Last Call</title><link>/2007/11/jingle-last-call</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; issued a last call for comments on the various Jingle specifications for multimedia negotiation over XMPP. Comments should be provided by December 14, so read the following specifications and send your feedback to the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/standards/"&gt;standards@xmpp.org&lt;/a&gt; list:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0166.html"&gt;Jingle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0167.html"&gt;Jingle Audio via RTP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0168.html"&gt;Resource Application Priority&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0176.html"&gt;Jingle ICE Transport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0177.html"&gt;Jingle Raw UDP Transport&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0180.html"&gt;Jingle Video via RTP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0181.html"&gt;Jingle DTMF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0208.html"&gt;Bootstrapping Implementation of Jingle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will soon also publish a specification for mapping between SIP and Jingle for seamless gatewaying of open multimedia technologies.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2007 13:52:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-11-21:2007/11/jingle-last-call</guid></item><item><title>What Is XMPP?</title><link>/2007/10/what-is-xmpp</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) is an open XML technology for real-time communication, which powers a wide range of applications including instant messaging, presence, media negotiation, whiteboarding, collaboration, lightweight middleware, content syndication, and generalized XML routing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More formally, XMPP is defined by &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3920.txt"&gt;RFC 3920&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3921.txt"&gt;RFC 3921&lt;/a&gt; as published by the IETF in October 2004. Everything we've built on top of those two specifications we call "XMPP extensions" (usually defined in the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/"&gt;XEP series&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the last year or so we've been working to incorporate feedback from the widespread implementation and deployment of XMPP technologies into the core definitions of XMPP. That has been happening through revisions to two Internet-Drafts at the IETF: &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-saintandre-rfc3920bis"&gt;draft-saintandre-rfc3920bis&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-saintandre-rfc3921bis"&gt;draft-saintandre-rfc3921bis&lt;/a&gt; . As part of that effort, we have also published a &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-xmpp-feature-set-00.html"&gt;protocol feature set&lt;/a&gt; that can be used when companies and open-source projects that have implemented XMPP submit interoperability reports to the IETF (based on a &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-newtrk-interop-reports-00"&gt;proposal&lt;/a&gt; by Larry Masinter in the IETF's NEWTRK Working Group).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These formal specifications are definitely not marketing documents! They are dry, boring, highly technical protocol definitions. But they provide the basis for all of our work with XMPP technologies, which is why it is so important to get the details right. Before we seek approval of the revised XMPP specifications within the IETF, broad review is needed from the full range of XMPP developers and community members, so if you have feedback please send it to the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/standards"&gt;standards@xmpp.org&lt;/a&gt; discussion list or to the document editor directly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 31 Oct 2007 10:53:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-10-31:2007/10/what-is-xmpp</guid></item><item><title>Summer of Code Success</title><link>/2007/10/summer-of-code-success</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Although the &lt;a href="http://blog.xmpp.org/?p=20"&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; ended weeks ago, we neglected to post a final summary. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the XMPP-related projects ended successfully and all of our students continue to contribute to the community. You can download their code &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/p/google-summer-of-code-2007-xmpp/downloads/list"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and you can view final project reports from our students at the following links:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://caustiq.esoteriq.org/nb/archives/2007/08/#e2007-08-19T21_56_08.txt"&gt;Armando Diaz-Jagucki on PEP support in the Openfire server&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://badlop.blogspot.com/2007/08/summary-of-my-gsoc-project.html"&gt;Bernardo Antonio de la Ossa Pérez on Extended Stanza Addressing support in the ejabberd server&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://necronomicorp.com/lab/31"&gt;Brendan Taylor on Encrypted Sessions support in the Gajim client&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://matthewstechnologyblog.blogspot.com/2007/09/summer-of-code-final-update.html"&gt;Matthew Wild on HTTP Binding / BOSH support in the gloox library&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://ayena.de/index.php?q=node/58"&gt;Tobias Markmann on his Data Forms designer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://liori.jogger.pl/2007/09/11/soc-summary/"&gt;Tomasz Melcer on Jingle support in the Gajim client&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations to all our students and thanks to all our mentors!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 02 Oct 2007 15:40:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-10-02:2007/10/summer-of-code-success</guid></item><item><title>Elections</title><link>/2007/08/elections</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Every year is an election for the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/"&gt;XMPP Standards Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, because since 2001 we have elected a new &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/council"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; (our technical leadership team) and a new &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/board/"&gt;Board of Directors&lt;/a&gt; (our business leadership team) in late August or September.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, this year is no exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As XSF Secretary Alexander Gnauck &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/members/2007-August/004461.html"&gt;recently announced&lt;/a&gt;, we will be holding our election meeting on September 27, although our online voting process will begin on September 8. In accordance with our &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/docs/bylaws.shtml"&gt;bylaws&lt;/a&gt;, any XSF member is welcome to stand for election to the Council, and any person is welcome to stand for election to the Board. Simply create an appropriate page on the &lt;a href="http://wiki.jabber.org/index.php/Board_and_Council_Elections_2007"&gt;wiki&lt;/a&gt; before September 7 and you will automatically be considered for election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're always looking for smart, dedicated people to serve on the Board and Council, so don't be shy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about the responsibilities and time commitments, feel free to ask any of the current or past Board and Council members, or talk with XSF Executive Director &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/people/stpeter.shtml"&gt;Peter Saint-Andre&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2007 15:50:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-08-15:2007/08/elections</guid></item><item><title>XSF Membership</title><link>/2007/07/xsf-membership</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/people/agnauck.shtml"&gt;Alexander Gnauck&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/secretary.shtml"&gt;Secretary&lt;/a&gt; of the XSF) posted a &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/jdev/2007-July/025504.html"&gt;notice&lt;/a&gt; about the Q3 membership application period. So this seems like a good occasion to explain a bit about how the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/"&gt;XMPP Standards Foundation&lt;/a&gt; works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The XSF is a non-profit, membership-based, standards-development organization. The non-profit part means that we're not here to make money. The standards-development part means that our &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/mission.shtml"&gt;mission&lt;/a&gt; is to produce open standards for communication over the Internet. The membership-based part means that we are run by the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/members/"&gt;elected members&lt;/a&gt; of the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some standards development organizations have members, but you must pay to become a member. Examples include the &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/"&gt;W3C&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.oasis-open.org/"&gt;OASIS&lt;/a&gt;. These organizations may do fine work and they may publish open standards, but their processes are essentially closed (unless you work for one of their member companies, you can't provide input to their standards processes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other standards development organizations, most particularly the &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/"&gt;IETF&lt;/a&gt;, are completely open (you count as a member of the IETF if you go to one of their meetings or participate on their mailing lists). The IETF has experienced some challenges and complications because of its anarchic nature, which the XSF avoids in part by having a more structured form of membership. Like the IETF, membership in the XSF applies to individuals, not companies (you can't buy your way in, and our standards-development &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/standards"&gt;discussion list&lt;/a&gt; is open to all interested individuals, not just elected members of the XSF). Unlike the IETF, the XSF has relatively few members, who are elected by the existing members four times a year based on individual merit rather than company connections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may seem that XSF members don't do much, and in a way that's true. Four times a year (January, April, July, and October), they elect new members and decide whether existing members shall remain members. Once a year (late August or early September) they elect a new &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; (our technical leadership group, all of whom must be elected members of the XSF) and a new &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/board/"&gt;Board of Directors&lt;/a&gt;. But the membership has ultimate responsibility for the direction of the organization because they can modify the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/docs/bylaws.shtml"&gt;Bylaws&lt;/a&gt;, remove Board members or other officers such as the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/director.shtml"&gt;Executive Director&lt;/a&gt;, and in general control the operation of the organization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In accordance with the meritocratic nature of most open-source projects (where the XSF has its roots), membership in the XSF is a privilege granted to individuals. In accordance with the developer-focused nature of the XSF, most of our members are coders who work on servers, clients, libraries, and other codebases that implement XMPP and various &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/"&gt;XMPP extensions&lt;/a&gt;. Some XSF members work for commercial software vendors. Some work on open-source projects or shareware code or freeware clients. But all of them have contributed in significant ways to the growth of Jabber/XMPP technologies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you build XMPP-based software or services and want to help maintain the XSF, we welcome you to &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/jdev/2007-July/025504.html"&gt;apply for membership&lt;/a&gt; before July 15.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2007 13:52:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-07-02:2007/07/xsf-membership</guid></item><item><title>Bonjour!</title><link>/2007/06/bonjour</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today we advanced &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0174.html"&gt;XEP-0174: Link-Local Messaging&lt;/a&gt; to Draft in our standards process. This specification defines how to send XMPP messages in a serverless mode via zero-configuration networking (a technology created by Apple Computer, originally called Rendezvous and now called Bonjour). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As &lt;a href="http://blog.xmpp.org/?p=14"&gt;previously mentioned&lt;/a&gt;, we issued a Last Call for comments on this specification on March 1. Feedback came in from a number of developers, resulting in some corrections late in the process, thus the delay in publication. But the spec is stronger for the feedback and we're looking forward to seeing implementations in more Jabber clients (e.g., there is a Google Summer of Code project to improve the link-local messaging support in the Adium client for Mac OS X).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everyone who provided comments on this spec!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jun 2007 12:58:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-06-12:2007/06/bonjour</guid></item><item><title>IETF Advancement</title><link>/2007/06/ietf-advancement</link><description>&lt;p&gt;As previously mentioned, we are working to update the core XMPP specifications by incorporating feedback based on the significant implementation and deployment experience with XMPP technologies we have gained since &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3920.txt"&gt;RFC 3920&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3921.txt"&gt;RFC 3921&lt;/a&gt; were published in October, 2004. To date we have expected the revised versions to advance XMPP to a status of Draft Standard within the &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2026.txt"&gt;Internet Standards Process&lt;/a&gt; managed by the IETF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it seems that we overlooked some of the rules from RFC 2026, specifically that "standards track specifications normally must not depend on other standards track specifications which are at a lower maturity level".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this means is that the XMPP specifications will not be able to advance to Draft until the specs defining IETF technologies on which XMPP depends also advance to Draft (i.e., until there are no more downward references or "downrefs").&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the XMPP specs have many downrefs, including the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2743.txt"&gt;RFC 2743: Generic Security Service Application Program Interface Version 2, Update 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2782.txt"&gt;RFC 2782: A DNS RR for specifying the location of services (DNS SRV)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2831.txt"&gt;RFC 2831: Using Digest Authentication as a SASL Mechanism&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3280.txt"&gt;RFC 3280: Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate and Certificate Revocation List (CRL) Profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3454.txt"&gt;RFC 3454: Preparation of Internationalized Strings ("stringprep")&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3490.txt"&gt;RFC 3490: Internationalizing Domain Names in Applications (IDNA)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3491.txt"&gt;RFC 3491: Nameprep: A Stringprep Profile for Internationalized Domain Names (IDN)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4122.txt"&gt;RFC 4122: A Universally Unique IDentifier (UUID) URN Namespace&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4346.txt"&gt;RFC 4346: The Transport Layer Security (TLS) Protocol Version 1.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4422.txt"&gt;RFC 4422: Simple Authentication and Security Layer (SASL)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4648.txt"&gt;RFC 4648: The Base16, Base32, and Base64 Data Encodings&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the serious number of significant downrefs, I think it's unrealistic for us to expect advancement of XMPP to Draft Standard anytime soon. It appears that the best we can do is update the XMPP specs as we have been doing, resulting in revised specifications that reflect our community's implementation and deployment experience but that are still at the Proposed Standard level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And speaking of updated specs, expect revised versions of &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-rfc3920bis-02.html"&gt;rfc3920bis&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-rfc3921bis-02.html"&gt;rfc3920bis&lt;/a&gt; soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPDATE: As &lt;a href="http://arch.jabber.com/2007/06/11/ietf-process/"&gt;Joe Hildebrand&lt;/a&gt; mentions (see also &lt;a href="http://stpeter.im/?p=1920"&gt;my reply&lt;/a&gt;), things are probably not quite so dire. Check for further updates as we work with folks at the IETF on this topic...&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jun 2007 12:59:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-06-11:2007/06/ietf-advancement</guid></item><item><title>XMPP DevCon #3</title><link>/2007/05/xmpp-devcon-3</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We've scheduled &lt;a href="http://wiki.jabber.org/index.php/DevCon"&gt;XMPP DevCon3&lt;/a&gt; for July 23 and 24, 2007, in Portland, Oregon, USA. Logistical details are being worked out right now, but save the dates if you're interested in brainstorming real-time applications with other XMPP developers in an informal, technology-focused environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for further updates in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2007 10:41:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-05-08:2007/05/xmpp-devcon-3</guid></item><item><title>Testing 1-2-3</title><link>/2007/05/testing-1-2-3</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/roadmap.shtml"&gt;roadmap&lt;/a&gt; items we discussed at the &lt;a href="http://blog.xmpp.org/?p=12"&gt;XMPP Summit&lt;/a&gt; in late February was the need to certify that XMPP clients and servers comply with our protocol specifications. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While eventually we would like to have a formal certification program, we recently have taken two steps toward that goal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/standards/2007-April/015073.html"&gt;publication&lt;/a&gt; of basic and intermediate certification levels for clients and servers in &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0211.html"&gt;XEP-0211&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0212.html"&gt;XEP-0212&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0213.html"&gt;XEP-0213&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The launch of the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/interop/"&gt;XMPP Interoperability Testing Network&lt;/a&gt;, a private network of servers that XMPP developers can use for testing their code against a wide range of server and client implementations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both of these efforts should begin to yield results in the next few months, resulting in a better, more consistent experience for end users and server administrators alike.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 May 2007 13:46:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-05-04:2007/05/testing-1-2-3</guid></item><item><title>XMPP URN Redux</title><link>/2007/04/xmpp-urn-redux</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Late yesterday the RFC Editor &lt;a href="http://www1.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/ietf-announce/current/msg03663.html"&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that the specification defining a URN namespace for use by the XMPP Standards Foundation has been published as &lt;a href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4854.txt"&gt;RFC 4854&lt;/a&gt;. See our &lt;a href="http://blog.xmpp.org/?p=13"&gt;previous post&lt;/a&gt; for background information.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2007 04:44:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-04-28:2007/04/xmpp-urn-redux</guid></item><item><title>Jingle Progress</title><link>/2007/04/jingle-progress</link><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the high-priority items on our &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/roadmap.shtml"&gt;roadmap&lt;/a&gt; for 2007 is completing work on &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0166.html"&gt;Jingle&lt;/a&gt;, the set of XMPP extensions for voice and video that we first published in late 2005. Although it's taken us about 16 months, we are getting &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/standards/2007-April/014927.html"&gt;quite close&lt;/a&gt; to advancing the Jingle specifications to Draft status within our standards process. Jingle, originally based on the technology defined by &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/talk/"&gt;Google Talk&lt;/a&gt; team, is now widely used in the &lt;a href="http://www.laptop.org/"&gt;One Laptop Per Child&lt;/a&gt; project as well as in the Nokia 770 and the Nokia 800.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we updated five of the main Jingle specs:&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0166.html"&gt;Jingle core&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0167.html"&gt;Jingle Audio via RTP&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0180.html"&gt;Jingle Video via RTP&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0176.html"&gt;Jingle ICE Transport&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0177.html"&gt;Jingle Raw UDP Transport&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These specs should be ready for Last Call very soon now, so stay tuned for further updates.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2007 18:52:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-04-17:2007/04/jingle-progress</guid></item><item><title>RFC Updates</title><link>/2007/04/rfc-updates</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We continue to make incremental modifications to &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3920.txt"&gt;RFC 3920&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3921.txt"&gt;RFC 3921&lt;/a&gt;, the core specifications of the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP). Most of these modifications are relatively minor clarifications or reflect implementation and deployment experience our community has gained since the XMPP RFCs were published in 2004.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we submitted updated ("-02") versions of &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-rfc3920bis-02.html"&gt;rfc3920bis&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-rfc3921bis-02.html"&gt;rfc3921bis&lt;/a&gt; to the IETF. The diffs from the "-01" versions are fairly small -- see &lt;a href="http://tinyurl.com/yrys6d"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://tinyurl.com/23v9dz"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for details.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2007 18:03:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-04-17:2007/04/rfc-updates</guid></item><item><title>Summer of Code Projects</title><link>/2007/04/summer-of-code-projects</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Google has announced the 2007 &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/"&gt;Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; projects, and the &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/xmpp/about.html"&gt;XSF projects&lt;/a&gt; are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=87181BA9B5E6306C"&gt;Bidirectional-streams Over Synchronous HTTP (BOSH) Support in gloox&lt;/a&gt; (Student: Matthew James Wild, Mentor: Jakob Schröter)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=5B4906B380FB37AB"&gt;Data Form Designer Suite for XMPP&lt;/a&gt; (Student: Tobias Markmann, Mentor: Kevin Smith)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=5AFC621F478B00ED"&gt;Encrypted Sessions Test Suite and Implementation&lt;/a&gt; (Student: Brendan Taylor, Mentor: Yann Le Boulanger)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=A765E8D6A159AA75"&gt;Extended Stanza Addressing and Other XEPs in ejabberd&lt;/a&gt; (Student: Bernardo Antonio de la Ossa Pérez, Mentor: Mickaël Rémond)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=611F6103CB37066C"&gt;Jingle Audio/Video in Gajim&lt;/a&gt; (Student: Tomasz Melcer, Mentor: Yann Le Boulanger)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/xmpp/appinfo.html?csaid=3E0E4A887EE8F266"&gt;Personal Eventing in Openfire&lt;/a&gt; (Student: Armando Diaz-Jagucki, Mentor: Gaston Dombiak)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's start coding!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2007 09:33:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-04-12:2007/04/summer-of-code-projects</guid></item><item><title>Presence Scalability</title><link>/2007/04/presence-scalability</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Members of the IETF's SIMPLE Working Group recently &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-simple-interdomain-scaling-analysis-00.txt"&gt;analyzed&lt;/a&gt; the scalability of SIP/SIMPLE technologies with respect to sharing presence between domains. Because their work provides a helpful baseline for comparing presence technologies, we decided to perform a &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-xmpp-presence-analysis-00.html"&gt;similar analysis&lt;/a&gt; for XMPP. The results should be of interest to any large enterprise, ISP, or carrier that is contemplating deployment of presence-based services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider some of the relevant results for bandwidth usage between two presence domains:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the domains have 20,000 users, where each user has 4 contacts in the other domain and changes presence 3 times an hour, bandwidth usage is estimated to be 30 kilobytes per second for XMPP and 830 kilobytes per second for SIMPLE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the domains have 20,000 users, where each user has 20 contacts in the other domain and changes presence 3 times an hour, bandwidth usage is estimated to be 150 kilobytes per second for XMPP and 1,968 kilobytes per second for SIMPLE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the domains have 60,000 users, where each user has 10 contacts in the other domain and changes presence 3 times an hour, bandwidth usage is estimated to be 225 kilobytes per second for XMPP and 3,683 kilobytes per second for SIMPLE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the domains have 10,000,000 users, where each user has 10 contacts in the other domain and changes presence 6 times an hour, bandwidth usage is estimated to be 70,833 kilobytes per second for XMPP and 880,555 kilobytes per second for SIMPLE.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While these analyses need to be reviewed, discussed, and extended within the IETF, the preliminary results indicate that the choice of presence technology can make a significant difference with regard to bandwidth usage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPDATE 2007-10-02: See &lt;a href="https://stpeter.im/?p=2051"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for more up-to-date analysis.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2007 15:27:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-04-11:2007/04/presence-scalability</guid></item><item><title>I-D Updates at the IETF</title><link>/2007/04/i-d-updates-at-the-ietf</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Although the XMPP Standards Foundation runs its own &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0001.html"&gt;standards process&lt;/a&gt; and publishes a dedicated &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/"&gt;specification series&lt;/a&gt; for XMPP extensions, we continue to work within the &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/"&gt;Internet Engineering Task Force&lt;/a&gt; on relevant specifications, which we &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/"&gt;mirror&lt;/a&gt; at xmpp.org for convenient access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lately we have updated several of the RFCs and Internet-Drafts we are working on within the IETF:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-rfc4622bis-00.html"&gt;draft-saintandre-rfc4622bis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this document corrects several errors in &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/rfcs/rfc4622.html"&gt;RFC 4622&lt;/a&gt;, which defines the
xmpp: URI scheme (a handy diff from RFC 4622 is &lt;a href="http://tools.ietf.org/rfcdiff?url1=http%3A%2F%2Ftools.ietf.org%2Frfc%2Frfc4622.txt&amp;amp;url2=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.xmpp.org%2Finternet-drafts%2Fdraft-saintandre-rfc4622bis-00.txt&amp;amp;difftype=--hwdiff"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http: www.xmpp.org internet-drafts draft-saintandre-jabberid-05.html"&gt;draft-saintandre-jabberid&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this document defines the &lt;a href="http://wiki.jabber.org/index.php/Jabber_Email_Header"&gt;Jabber-ID email header&lt;/a&gt;, which enables you to specify your XMPP address in the email messages you send&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-xmpp-simple-09.html"&gt;draft-saintandre-xmpp-simple&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this document, which describes interworking between XMPP and SIMPLE for basic IM and presence, shows our continued commitment to open communication (an &lt;a href="http://www1.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/simple/current/msg07146.html"&gt;informal last call&lt;/a&gt; is in progress on the discussion list of the IETF's &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/simple-charter.html"&gt;SIMPLE WG&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-sieve-notify-xmpp-04.html"&gt;draft-ietf-sieve-notify-xmpp&lt;/a&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;this document, an official work item of the IETF's &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/html.charters/sieve-charter.html"&gt;Sieve WG&lt;/a&gt;, defines how to generate XMPP notifications for receipt of new email (and more) using the &lt;a href="http://www.fastmail.fm/docs/sieve/index.html"&gt;Sieve&lt;/a&gt; email filtering language&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And look for some relatively slight modifications to &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-rfc3920bis-01.html"&gt;rfc3920bis&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-rfc3921bis-01.html"&gt;rfc3921bis&lt;/a&gt; soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2007 11:22:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-04-11:2007/04/i-d-updates-at-the-ietf</guid></item><item><title>XMPP Eventing via Pubsub</title><link>/2007/04/xmpp-eventing-via-pubsub</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Following in the grand tradition of &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0076.html"&gt;XEP-0076&lt;/a&gt; (implementation in the Psi client &lt;a href="http://el-tramo.be/blog/malicious-stanzas"&gt;announced today&lt;/a&gt;), &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0132.html"&gt;XEP-0132&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0148.html"&gt;XEP-0148&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0183.html"&gt;XEP-0183&lt;/a&gt;, today we published &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0207.html"&gt;XEP-0207: XMPP Eventing via Pubsub (XEP)&lt;/a&gt;. This new "XEP XEP" is perhaps the most significant XMPP extension protocol yet published by the XMPP Standards Foundation, since it provides a solid, extensible foundation for any further payloads we might want to send over the network. &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0207.html"&gt;Read the spec&lt;/a&gt; for complete details.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 01 Apr 2007 13:41:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-04-01:2007/04/xmpp-eventing-via-pubsub</guid></item><item><title>Summer by the (XML) Stream</title><link>/2007/03/summer-by-the-xml-stream</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/"&gt;XMPP Standards Foundation&lt;/a&gt; will once again be &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/xmpp/about.html"&gt;participating&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href="http://code.google.com/soc/"&gt;Google Summer of Code&lt;/a&gt; for 2007. What is a standards organization doing in the Summer of Code? Well, the Extensible Messaging and Presence Protocol (XMPP) emerged from the Jabber open-source community and we still have many active open-source projects. Plus as &lt;a href="http://blog.xmpp.org/?p=12"&gt;previously mentioned&lt;/a&gt; our community is a cohesive blend of open standards, commercial organizations, and open-source developers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here at the XSF we usually focus on the open standards part of the equation, but we actively work to encourage the creation of open-source code, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So check out out &lt;a href="http://wiki.jabber.org/index.php/Summer_of_Code_2007"&gt;project ideas&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://groups.google.com/group/google-summer-of-code-announce/web/guide-to-the-gsoc-web-app-for-student-applicants"&gt;send in an application&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPDATE: If you apply, ignore the mention of the application template -- you do not need to fill that out in order to apply!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Mar 2007 19:19:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-03-20:2007/03/summer-by-the-xml-stream</guid></item><item><title>Freedom</title><link>/2007/03/freedom</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Freedom is one of our core values in the Jabber/XMPP community. The focus on freedom goes back to &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/people/jer.shtml"&gt;Jeremie Miller&lt;/a&gt;, who invented the base of our technologies in 1998 as a way for people to connect over the Internet without the silos and restrictions enforced by consumer IM services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over the years that sense of freedom has broadened and deepened. Consider:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our community has centered on Internet protocols (not a given open-source codebase) in part to give developers the freedom to use whatever license they want: free source, open source, freeware, shareware, commercial, or any combination thereof.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our protocols are as free as the air, which means anyone may implement them without asking permission or worrying about patents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our protocols are pure XML, which means developers may extend the protocols for their own custom functionality. While we standardize &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions"&gt;XMPP extensions&lt;/a&gt; that are of more general interest, developers have the freedom to make their own extensions and not standardize them through the XSF if they don't want to.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As &lt;a href="http://blog.xmpp.org/?p=9"&gt;previously mentioned&lt;/a&gt;, all of our discussion venues and processes are completely open and transparent, giving any individual the freedom to participate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our technologies are designed to enable organizations to connect their XMPP servers for inter-domain federation if desired, but they also have the freedom to run a server behind the firewall without connecting to other domains.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Individuals who use Jabber/XMPP technologies for instant messaging still have the fundamental freedom of conversation that Jeremie envisioned back in 1998.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So freedom is more than just a pleasant word or "value statement" for us -- it is a way of life and a key part of everything we are working to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2007 13:06:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-03-06:2007/03/freedom</guid></item><item><title>Last Call: Link-Local Messaging</title><link>/2007/03/last-call-link-local-messaging</link><description>&lt;p&gt;At the XMPP Summit on Monday we held a rare in-person meeting of the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt;, since we had four of the five Council members in attendance. Among other things the Council issued a &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/standards/2007-February/014012.html"&gt;Last Call&lt;/a&gt; for comments on &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0174.html"&gt;XEP-0174: Link-Local Messaging&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This technology, which enables real-time messaging in the absence of a server, was pioneered by Apple in an early version of their &lt;a href="http://www.apple.com/ichat/"&gt;iChat&lt;/a&gt; client. It has since been adopted in several open-source instant messaging clients and is now also widely used in the &lt;a href="http://www.laptop.org/"&gt;One Laptop Per Child&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although this serverless mode is not precisely an XMPP extension since XMPP as defined in &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/rfcs/rfc3920.html"&gt;RFC 3920&lt;/a&gt; requires a server for authentication and network access, it does re-use XMPP's XML streams for peer-to-peer communication in a local mesh, so it seemed appropriate to standardize its usage through the XMPP Standards Foundation. The spec has been stable for some time and now appears mature enough to advance to Draft within our standards process. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Last Call ends on 2007-03-13, so if you have comments send them as always to our open &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/standards"&gt;standards discussion list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2007 19:53:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-03-01:2007/03/last-call-link-local-messaging</guid></item><item><title>XMPP URNs</title><link>/2007/02/xmpp-urns</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Yesterday the IETF &lt;a href="http://www1.ietf.org/mail-archive/web/ietf-announce/current/msg03462.html"&gt;announced&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-xmpp-urn-03.html"&gt;draft-saintandre-xmpp-urn&lt;/a&gt; has been approved by the &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/iesg.html"&gt;IESG&lt;/a&gt; for publication as an informational RFC. What this means for us is that the XSF (specifically the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/registrar/"&gt;XMPP Registrar&lt;/a&gt;) will control its own "tree" of &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2141.txt"&gt;Uniform Resource Names&lt;/a&gt; to issue for use in &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/"&gt;XMPP Extension Protocols&lt;/a&gt;, as specified in Section 4 of &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0053.html"&gt;XEP-0053&lt;/a&gt;. This is good because URNs are more stable than the URIs (such as "http://jabber.org/protocol/muc") that we've been using for XML namespaces in our protocols. Although we lose the ability to copy and paste such a URI into a browser and find information about the relevant protocol, it's easy enough to search for a string like "urn:xmpp:chatneg" and find the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0155.html"&gt;relevant specification&lt;/a&gt;. So the slight loss in convenience is offset by the improved permanence of our XML namespaces. Besides, all the other standards development organizations are using URNs, so why not us? :-)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UPDATE 2007-04-28: This document has now been published as &lt;a href="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/rfc4854.txt"&gt;RFC 4854&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2007 11:45:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-02-28:2007/02/xmpp-urns</guid></item><item><title>Brussels Report</title><link>/2007/02/brussels-report</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Over the weekend, members of the XMPP Standards Foundation and the Jabber developer community participated in &lt;a href="http://www.fosdem.org/"&gt;FOSDEM 2007&lt;/a&gt; (one of the world's premier conferences for developers of free and open-source software) and also held a smaller "XMPP Summit" to discuss high-priority issues related to our technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it's safe to say that the weekend was a smashing success. Our developer room at FOSDEM hosted a full schedule of talks and was often standing room only. Topics included virtual presence, Jingle, telephony integration, mobile applications, server and client architecture, transporting XMPP over HTTP connections, and hacking XMPP applications with the Twisted Python library. I also gave a talk in the main track on secure communications (video footage is &lt;a href="http://www.fosdem.org/2007/media/video"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), in which I discussed our recent security work and announced our partnership with &lt;a href="http://www.nlnet.nl/"&gt;NLnet&lt;/a&gt; to make end-to-end encryption a reality on our network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the Monday after FOSDEM, we held an "XMPP Summit" attended by four of the five &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; members, all three &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/board/"&gt;XSF Board&lt;/a&gt; members, and half a dozen developers from the community. Good progress was made on various &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/roadmap.shtml"&gt;roadmap&lt;/a&gt; topics such as Jingle, end-to-end encryption, Personal Eventing Protocol, message archiving, file transfer, and shared roster (a.k.a. "communities"). The group also discussed methods for building a software certification program to encourage implementation of important XMPP extensions. Expect further updates regarding these initiatives in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As always, some of the most interesting technical conversations occurred in conference hallways, restaurants, and pubs. Developers who have worked together for years over the Internet -- sometimes even on the same project -- got a chance to meet IRL (that's "in real life" for you non-IM people). During one of those conversations, XMPP Council member Ralph Meijer made an insightful observation: ours seems to be the only coherent, vibrant technology community that is centered on a protocol rather than a codebase. There is not really an HTTP community or SMTP community or SIP community, in the sense of a group of open-source and commercial developers, technology architects, and users who over many years have regularly and openly communicated and cooperated on solving technical problems together. But somehow we seem to have achieved that rare feat in the Jabber/XMPP community, and it is a large part of our strength and longevity. Events such as our weekend in Brussels further reinforce the sinews of our community, which is why they are so important to the progress of our technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And lest I forget, special thanks are due to the following individuals for their help in making this weekend so productive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ralph Meijer for organizing our FOSDEM developer room&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Edwin Mons and Christ van Willegen for manning our &lt;a href="http://flickr.com/photos/nukeador/404681293/"&gt;FOSDEM
    booth&lt;/a&gt; and for much
    logistical help&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mickaël Rémond for arranging meeting space for the XMPP Summit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See you in Brussels for FOSDEM 2008!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2007 20:14:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-02-27:2007/02/brussels-report</guid></item><item><title>Practicing What We Preach</title><link>/2007/02/practicing-what-we-preach</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Because the XSF is a standards development organization, we strive to honor standards developed by other organizations. To that end, we recently updated the web pages at &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/"&gt;www.xmpp.org&lt;/a&gt; (including our &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/"&gt;specification series&lt;/a&gt;) to comply with &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml1/"&gt;XHTML 1.0&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you find a page with an "xhtml 1.0 compliant" link at the bottom but the page does not &lt;a href="http://validator.w3.org/"&gt;validate&lt;/a&gt;, please report the error to webmaster at xmpp.org.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2007 22:23:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-02-15:2007/02/practicing-what-we-preach</guid></item><item><title>Purposes</title><link>/2007/02/purposes</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In preparing an application for the XSF to officially achieve tax-exempt status with the U.S. Internal Revenue Service, we discovered today that the original certificate of incorporation defined the organization as a "business league" under Section 501(c)(6) of the Internal Revenue Code, rather than as an "educational, charitable and scientific organization" under Section 501(c)(3).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reasons for the original choice of purpose are lost in the mists of time, but in any case are not consistent with the focus of the organization over the last five years on standards development. Therefore this seems like a good time to clarify the purposes of the XSF through an official amendment to the certificate of incorporation. The initial version of a proposal to do just that is located &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/proposals/purpose-proposal.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and may be voted on by the XSF membership in the next few weeks (once it has been discussed and improved on the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/members/"&gt;publicly-archived&lt;/a&gt; discussion list for XSF members).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feedback is welcome as always -- use the comment form here at the blog or contact the proposal author directly via email or IM.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2007 20:39:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-02-12:2007/02/purposes</guid></item><item><title>Be Open</title><link>/2007/02/be-open</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We sometimes receive questions about whether there are restrictions on who may submit and comment on &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/"&gt;proposals&lt;/a&gt; to extend XMPP, join the various XMPP-related &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/about/discuss.shtml"&gt;discussion venues&lt;/a&gt;, or participate in events such as our upcoming &lt;a href="http://wiki.jabber.org/index.php/DevCon"&gt;DevCon&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The short answer is: No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The long answer is that we strive to be a completely open and transparent community. Unlike some standards development organizations that call themselves open but are in fact industry consortia with closed processes and high barriers to entry, the XMPP Standards Foundation is fully committed to openness. Although we have elected &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/members/"&gt;members&lt;/a&gt; and generous &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/sponsors/"&gt;sponsors&lt;/a&gt;, they merely provide the legal and financial basis for us to pursue our work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps because our technology emerged from the open-source community, we think that the philosophy of "with enough eyeballs, all bugs are shallow" applies just as much to protocols as it does to code. That's why all of our protocol discussions take place on an &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/standards"&gt;open discussion list&lt;/a&gt;. That's why we publish the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/council/agendas/"&gt;agendas&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.jabber.org/muc-logs/council@conference.jabber.org/"&gt;chat logs&lt;/a&gt; of the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/council/"&gt;XMPP Council&lt;/a&gt; for all to see. That's why we keep all of our specifications (and in fact our entire website) under &lt;a href="http://www.jabberstudio.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/cvs/xmpp/"&gt;source control&lt;/a&gt; so you can see exactly what we change. And that's why you don't need to be an elected member or an employee of a sponsoring company in order to participate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you or your organization builds XMPP-based technology, we encourage you to &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/about/discuss.shtml"&gt;join the conversation&lt;/a&gt;. It's the only way we can achieve our &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/mission.shtml"&gt;mission&lt;/a&gt; of building an open, standardized, secure, feature-rich, widely-deployed, decentralized infrastructure for real-time communication and collaboration over the Internet.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2007 21:22:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-02-09:2007/02/be-open</guid></item><item><title>Practical Network Security</title><link>/2007/02/practical-network-security</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Two months ago we launched the XMPP Intermediate Certification Authority at &lt;a href="https://www.xmpp.net/"&gt;xmpp.net&lt;/a&gt;. It was a bit of an unusual step for a standards development organization to take -- after all, you don't see the &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/"&gt;IETF&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/"&gt;W3C&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="http://www.imc.org/"&gt;IMC&lt;/a&gt; offering free digital certificates to hostmasters, webmasters, and postmasters. But we decided that we needed provide some practical leadership regarding the security of the Jabber/XMPP network, and &lt;a href="http://cert.startcom.org/"&gt;StartCom&lt;/a&gt; (our root CA) has made that task much easier than we could have hoped.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the results so far:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have issued around 100 active server certificates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have stabilized the certificate data format based on feedback from server admins and developers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several large XMPP-based code projects have built in support for StartCom's root certificate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More widespread deployment has exposed incorrect certificate handling in several software codebases, leading to bug fixes and more secure code.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clearly we have much farther to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we'd like to see all server and client codebases support &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4346.txt"&gt;TLS&lt;/a&gt; for channel security, &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4422.txt"&gt;SASL&lt;/a&gt; for strong authentication, and the StartCom root certificate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, we need many more server deployments to obtain digital certificates. In the past that has been an expensive proposition, but now the XSF provides no-cost ("free as in beer") digital certificates so there's no excuse! By the end of 2007 we hope that a majority of the traffic on the XMPP network will be protected by channel encryption. But to make that happen we need server admins to visit &lt;a href="https://www.xmpp.net/"&gt;xmpp.net&lt;/a&gt;, sign up for an account, and request a free certificate by following our simple &lt;a href="https://www.xmpp.net/certificate-process"&gt;certificate process&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, it's easy, it's fun, and it makes the network more secure, one server at a time!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2007 12:29:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-02-07:2007/02/practical-network-security</guid></item><item><title>Last Call: SASL EXTERNAL</title><link>/2007/01/last-call-sasl-external</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today we &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/pipermail/standards/2007-January/013676.html"&gt;issued&lt;/a&gt; a Last Call regarding &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/xep-0178.html"&gt;XEP-0178: Best Practices for Use of SASL EXTERNAL&lt;/a&gt;. This specification is part of our &lt;a href="http://blog.xmpp.org/?p=4"&gt;continuing effort&lt;/a&gt; to advance the XMPP RFCs to Draft Standard within the IETF.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although XEP-0178 does not contain any proposed changes to &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/rfcs/rfc3920.html"&gt;RFC 3920&lt;/a&gt; for inclusion in &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-rfc3920bis-01.html"&gt;rfc3920bis&lt;/a&gt;, it does document best practices regarding a particular &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc4422.txt"&gt;SASL&lt;/a&gt; authentication mechanism, in particular the SASL EXTERNAL mechanism as it relates to the X.509 public key infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We've gained quite a bit of experience with SASL EXTERNAL recently given our &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/press/2006-12-06.shtml"&gt;launch&lt;/a&gt; of an &lt;a href="https://www.xmpp.net/"&gt;intermediate certification authority&lt;/a&gt; for the XMPP network, and XEP-0178 incorporates some lessons learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Last Call ends 2007-02-13, so if you see any problems with the spec send feedback to the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/standards"&gt;standards discussion list&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2007 16:56:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-01-31:2007/01/last-call-sasl-external</guid></item><item><title>Continuing the Conversation at the IETF</title><link>/2007/01/continuing-the-conversation-at-the-ietf</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today we sent to the &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/"&gt;IETF&lt;/a&gt; updated versions of our proposed revisions to &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3920.txt"&gt;RFC 3920&lt;/a&gt; ("XMPP Core") and &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3921.txt"&gt;RFC 3921&lt;/a&gt; ("XMPP IM"). For reasons that are obscure to people outside the IETF, such revised documents are called "bis" drafts, so the documents in question are called &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-rfc3920bis-01.html"&gt;rfc3920bis&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/internet-drafts/draft-saintandre-rfc3921bis-01.html"&gt;rfc3921bis&lt;/a&gt;. These Internet-Drafts incorporate corrections, errata, updates to technologies we use (such as Transport Layer Security), feedback from implementors, interoperability testing results, and general lessons learned since the XMPP RFCs were published in October 2004.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the "delta" between the existing RFCs and the new documents is small enough that we won't need to change the version from XMPP 1.0 to XMPP 1.1, it is important to document the differences and update the specifications since they form the bedrock of our technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These Internet-Drafts will probably undergo one or two more rounds of revision (with increasingly minor changes), then we will ask the &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/iesg/"&gt;IESG&lt;/a&gt; to consider them for approval. Upon approval, they will be published with new RFC numbers (not 3920 and 3921) and, we expect, thus advance the core XMPP protocols from Proposed Standard to Draft Standard within the Internet Standards Process. Many Internet protocols never advance beyond Proposed Standard, but we take the Internet Standards Process seriously and would like XMPP to eventually become a final standard on par with TCP, IP, HTTP, SMTP, and other such foundational building blocks for the Internet as we know it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/roadmap.shtml"&gt;goal&lt;/a&gt; is to advance XMPP to Draft Standard before the end of 2007. Feedback from implementors is key to that effort, which is why we will be holding two interoperability testing events this year (the &lt;a href="http://wiki.jabber.org/index.php/Interop_Event'"&gt;next one&lt;/a&gt; in late February in Brussels).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Close review of the proposed revisions is also appreciated, with discussion occurring on the &lt;a href="http://mail.jabber.org/mailman/listinfo/xmppwg/"&gt;XMPPWG&lt;/a&gt; mailing list. As always, our events and discussion venues are completely open to contributions from any interested party (the XMPP Standards Foundation, like the IETF itself, is not a closed industry consortium but an open technology forum), so feel free to join the conversation and help us make XMPP as solid and secure as possible.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2007 19:43:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-01-26:2007/01/continuing-the-conversation-at-the-ietf</guid></item><item><title>Starting the Conversation</title><link>/2007/01/starting-the-conversation</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to Extended Conversation, the official weblog of the &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/xsf/"&gt;XMPP Standards Foundation&lt;/a&gt; (XSF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although many members of the Jabber/XMPP community have their own individual blogs (syndicated at &lt;a href="http://planet.jabber.org/"&gt;Planet Jabber&lt;/a&gt;), here we will post news and views from the XSF itself: information about XMPP-related standards work within the &lt;a href="http://www.ietf.org/"&gt;IETF&lt;/a&gt;, notices about &lt;a href="http://www.xmpp.org/extensions/"&gt;XMPP extensions&lt;/a&gt; that have been published or advanced within the XSF, updates about XSF initiatives such as the &lt;a href="https://www.xmpp.net/"&gt;intermediate certification authority&lt;/a&gt;, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those who develop Jabber/XMPP technologies have long cherished both freedom of conversation and the ability to extend those technologies in innovative ways, and we will continue that tradition here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So welcome -- and let's continue the conversation together!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">stpeter</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2007 11:41:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-01-23:2007/01/starting-the-conversation</guid></item></channel></rss>